<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.005" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Lecture I</title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="jh">Harper, Jordan</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="project">hta.005</idno>
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-02"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<pb facs="hta.005.001"/>

    <head>LECTURES,<lb/>
        &amp;c.</head>
        <head type="sub">LECTURE I.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, I. I.</bibl>
        <hi rend="italic">In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth.</hi></head>
        
    <p>HE who studies history aright, makes himself wise by the experience of others; and whosoever devotes a due portion of his researches to the authentic history of the creation, may make himself thereby wise to everlasting salvation. The object of such study is to ascertain the difference between Christianity and any other religion. Now the difference hetween Christianity and all other religions, as an eminent divine has correctly stated, is, that the latter are the result of human invention, whilst the former rests on revelation alone. Again, the mark which, we humbly trust, may be said to distinguish a reformed Christianity, is, that its professors and disciples have been careful and correct in <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.005.002"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice> the undoubted word of God, and separating it from those precepts, principles, and institutions (however recommended by antiquity, or endeared by custom), which have proceeded from the well-meant but superstitious piety of man, and are unconsecrated by any test of inspiration.</p>
    <p>Thanks to the learning, the piety, and the fortitude of our predecessors in the Church, we have liberal access to genuine and authenticated versions of Holy Writ. It is a privilege of which we may boast&#8212;it is a privilege, also, which may work our shame and condemnation, if we do not avail ourselves of it. Our Lord said unto the perverse Jews, "Verily, if ye were blind, ye should have no sin; but now ye say, We see; therefore your sin remaineth." So, in like manner, had it not pleased God to accord unto us the means of unlimited instruction in all that appertains to salvation, we should have shared in the excuse, by sharing in the ignorance which envelops many a people calling itself Christian. But now are we inexcusable, my beloved friends, if we refuse to drink the living waters of truth at their purest source. Of all studies, that of the Scriptures will be found most delightful, if judged of by the effects produced on the hearts, tempers, understandings, and morals of those who persevere</p>


</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


