<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.006" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Lecture II</title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="jh">Harper, Jordan</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="project">hta.006</idno>
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-03"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

    <pb facs="hta.006.001"/>
    
    <head>LECTURE II.</head>
        <head type="sub">LECTURE I.</head>
        <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, III. PART OF VER. 3.</bibl>
        <hi rend="italic">God hath said, Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die.</hi></head>
    
    <p>Such was the answer which Eve, the mother of human kind, gave to the serpent, when he first suggested to her the possibility of disobeying God, by asking that subtle question, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q001" source="kjv">"Hath God said, Ye shall not eat of every tree of the garden?"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q001" resp="#eds">Genesis 3:1</bibl></p>
    <p>Moses has detailed the circumstances of man's fall with most remarkable brevity-with precisely that imposing and authoritative brevity, which becomes him who wrote under inspiration, and who, consequently, felt sure that God would annex to the narrative that irresistible force of persuasion, which no descriptive power of human eloquence could attain. Therefore, obscure as the account might have appeared to those who were desirous of gainsaying, as the Israelites often showed themselves to be, yet we do not find that they, in their most factious moods, ever entertained a doubt of the
    
     <pb facs="hta.006.002"/>
    
    veracity of the Mosaic record. We have testimonies to its truth, which they could not have; we live after the complete fulfilment of many a prophecy, which neither they nor their children heard even with their outward ears. On us are come the ends of the world, and therefore have we been favored with a clearer knowledge of its beginnings.</p>
    <p>God having created man and woman, placed them in the garden of Eden. As man was made after the image of God, and, therefore, designed for immortality, no doubt can exist that every other part of creation was equally without spot or blemish. Indeed, it is expressly said, that God saw that all was good. Man, therefore, was richly, regularly, and spontaneously supplied with every thing that the earth and elements could produce. He had no wants unsatisfied, no hopes deferred by the difficulty or delay of attainment. The duration of such gratifications would have been as boundless as their extent, had he kept the only commandment which his Creator had given him. This commandment was simply, that he should not eat of the fruit of one particular tree, under penalty of immediate death. This tree is called by Moses, the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. It is of no importance to us to know (and assuredly we cannot ascertain), whether the fruit of
    
      <pb facs="hta.006.003"/>
        
        this tree was forbidden on account of its pernicious quality, or merely as a test of obedience. Under the latter supposition, the lesson proposed is sufficiently profitable. We may of a surety learn, that pride of heart occasioned the first falling off of man from God's law, and thence be made more vigilant, lest the same pride of heart be our chief impediment in a return to obedience. Although in the beginning of the third chapter of Genesis, it is simply stated, that the serpent, being the most subtile of animals, suggested to the woman, that she would be a gainer by breaking God's commandment; yet we are to understand from many concurrent inferences of reason, as well as from the general interpretation of this statement by many inspired writers, that Satan, that evil spirit, who, according to the Revelation of St. John, had already been cast out from heaven for rebellion against the Most High, made an instrument of the serpent. That some unnatural and prevailing agency must have been employed to excite a brute to speech, is obvious; for there is no shadow of reason to suppose, that such a privilege was ever conceded to any except human beings. That such a supernatural agency could not be of God, was evident; for it was exerted in disparagement of his previous ordinance. It follows, therefore, that the serpent was the vehicle
    
      <pb facs="hta.006.004"/>
    
    of an evil spirit. If it be objected, that Eve ought herself to have testified surprise at the novel circumstance of speech from a serpent, he it remembered, that she herself was too lately created, was surrounded with too numerous an assemblage of recent wonders, to form any accurate judgment on the laws of nature, or to be justified in astonishment at any mystery of the ensuing moment. Of much she might be ignornnt&#8212;of one thing she was well aware; and the text informs us that she was: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q002" source="kjv">"God hath said, Ye shall not eat of it, neither shall ye touch it, lest ye die."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q002" resp="#eds">Genesis 3:3</bibl> This puts her guilt beyond all question, as it might have done beyond all mercy. She, however, did not add denial to disobedience: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q003" source="kjv">"The serpent beguiled me, and I did eat."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q003" resp="#eds">Genesis 3:13</bibl> Look we well to ourselves, my brethren, lest we be beguiled of our innocence, of that true simplicity of heart which putteth to shame the wisdom of the wise, and glories in the avowal that Scripture was written for our learning. Till human reason can discover some more probable theory for the creation and fall of man, than the Mosaic narrative as above explained, all those are yet beguiled by the serpent who refuse their assent to what is in strict analogy with every promise, prophecy, and miracle, from the condemnation in Paradise to the ministry of the Apostles.</p>

    <pb facs="hta.006.005"/>
    
    <p>Having, on a former occasion<ref target="#hta.006.n01"></ref>, endeavoured to rectify any false and impious sentiment on the subject of man's offence, which might suggest that his sentence was severer than his crime deserved, I shall now merely observe, once for all, that his crime was wilful disobedience; and that God had previously pronounced the inseparable doom: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q004" source="kjv">"In the hour that thou eatest thereof thou shalt surely die."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q004" resp="#eds">Genesis 2:17</bibl> Nor are we here to entertain any doubt of God's veracity or consistency, because Adam and Eve did not die, in our vulgar sense of death, at the moment of their sin. From the moment of their sin their doom was fixed, the power of death made them captive. The principle of decay mixed itself with that frame which had been made in the image of God, and all power of immortality was denied to the body of man&#8212;<quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q005" source="kjv">"To dust thou shalt return."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q005" resp="#eds">Genesis 3:19</bibl> These words being pronounced as a just sentence of punishment, we must suppose, that, but for his disobedience, man would not have experienced death; and that, therefore, a thorough change took place in all his corporeal frame, from the very moment that he tasted the forbidden fruit. This is precisely what St. Paul infers, when he says, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q006" source="kjv">"By one man sin entered into the world, and
    
    <note xml:id="hta.006.n01">Allusion to a sermon preached on the morning of the
        preceding Sunday.</note> <!--how to tag a footnote-->

    <pb facs="hta.006.006"/>
    
    death by sin"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q006" resp="#eds">Romans 5:12</bibl>&#8212;and, again, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q007" source="kjv">"In Adam all die."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q007" resp="#eds">1 Corinthians 15:22</bibl> With the actual entrance of mortality into the human frame, there entered in a disposition towards every crime; so that death may impartially be regarded as the proper and providential avenger of sin, whilst it is a1so the necessary period of decay. Had the Almighty cut off Adam and Eve from the face of the earth at the moment of their offence, his justice would not have been marked with those signal proofs which are now exhibited, in the weakness, sorrow, and sufferings of all their descendants. Satan might then have boasted himself of having triumphed for ever, nor feared the enmity of the woman's seed; but God regardeth mercy, even in the awful career of his inflexible justice. Whilst he announced to our guilty parents their impending doom, he also regarded their penitence, and cheered the profound darkness of the future, by one celestial ray of light and life. He not only condemned the serpent to crawl and eat the dust, thereby signifying, that the powers of hell should ever be confined to fraud and artifice; but he predicted, that ultimately the "seed of the woman" should bruise the serpent's head. This was fully accomplished, when Christ having in the flesh performed that wherein Adam failed, having done the perfect will of God, visited the
   
        <pb facs="hta.006.007"/>
    
    grave without seeing corruption, and opened the everlasting doors of life by his resurrection.</p>
    <p>However Adam and Eve may be considered as having been temporarily reprieved, they were in no sense pardoned. For their sake creation was visited with a curse&#8212;the earth brought forth thistles, and man was condemned, by the labor of his hands and the sweat of his brow, to eke out the precarious remainder of a life, which should lead through the pangs of disease to the penalty of death. Surely those who contend that the heart of man is not naturally depraved, have never duly considered the contents of the fourth chapter of Genesis.  Surely they forget that the first crime recited, after man's expulsion from Paradise, is murder, is fratricide&#8212;the murder of one who fell by the hand of an only brother; and that they were the offspring of him who had been created in the image of God, and who, in the days of innocence, had communed with his Maker.</p>
    <p>The circumstances to which I shall chiefly request your attention in the melancholy history of Cain and Abel are these: Cain was displeased because his offering was rejected of God, while the offering of Abel was accepted. What excess of presumption! How instantaneously does the pride of man's heart, that
    
        <pb facs="hta.006.008"/>
    
    truly unchristian principle, burst out! Ought not Cain rather to have considered why his offering was rejected?&#8212;And why was his offering rejected? It is worth our thought; for the Almighty is not capricious; his ways are equal, though our ways are unequa1.</p>
    <p>Two reasons may be assigned&#8212;the one commonly assigned is this: Cain is supposed not to have tendered his offering in a proper disposition of mind; he seems to have demanded the acknowledgment, not solicited the favour of God; and that this was the case we collect from the sequel. There does, however, suggest itself another great neglect on the part of Cain, there was a specific difference in the nature of the thing offered, of which the historian makes minute mention. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q008" source="kjv">"Cain brought of the fruit of the ground an offering unto the Lord; and Abel, he brought of the firstlings of his flock."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q008" resp="#eds">Genesis 4:3-4</bibl> Now, remember what the Apostle saith, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.006.q009" source="kjv">"Without shedding of blood there can be no remission of sin."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.006.q009" resp="#eds">Hebrews 9:22</bibl> No doubt, this law was part of the first ordinance; and the authority under which they began to offer sacrifices, had simultaneously indicated to them the mysterious obligation of offering up an animated victim. With this great fundamental truth before our eyes, we understand why Cain's offering of first fruits was rejected, and why his brother was
    
       <pb facs="hta.006.009"/>
        
        called the <hi rend="italic">righteous</hi> Abel, although history hath recorded of him no other circumstance than that he offered unto the Lord the firstlings of his flock. We cannot render our perusal of Holy Writ more beneficial and satisfactory than by thus endeavouring to trace out beneath the surface of the narrative, those latent allusions to that great sacrifice of the Son of Man, predestined from the beginning of the world. Of this we have another memorial in the death of Abel himself. He is called <hi rend="italic">righteous</hi>&#8212;and he was the first victim to religion under the hands of violence and ungodliness.</p>
    <p>God is said to have set a mark upon Cain. On this subject various opinions have existed, and many inquiries been instituted as to the nature of the mark: such inquiries can seldom be recompensed by any accurate result. It does certainly appear to have been some distinction, which extended to Cain's posterity. In a subsequent chapter, these are called the daughters of men, in opposition to the sons of God, who were the descendants of Seth, <hi rend="italic">that</hi> child of Adam, who was appointed by God to supply the place of Abel. The inauspicious union of the sons of God with these seductive daughters of Cain and his tribe, spread on the face of the whole earth a general corruption,
    
    <pb facs="hta.006.010"/>
    
    and consigned man to the awful visitation of an universal deluge.</p>
    <p>I will now close my Lecture, remarking from the latter circumstances: 1st, That nothing next to connubial fidelity, is so amiable, so honourable, so replete with good to man, so lovely in the sight of God, as brotherly affection: 2dly, That it is of unspeakable importance, that those who have been brought up in the nurture of such angelic feelings, and every attendant virtue, should not disappoint the hopes of their parents, the interests of religion, and the prospects of their own eternal happiness, by inconsiderately connecting themselves indissolubly with any, however high in station, or attractive in appearance, who are conformed to a lower standard of morals, and who have not yet been called to a knowledge of salvation in Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
    
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


