<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.010" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="hb">Borrell, Hannah</name> <!-- if you are not Jordan Harper, change to your initials and name -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
    <idno type="project">hta.010</idno> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-02"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change> <!-- replace with correct name and date -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<!-- transcribe lecture here -->
    <!-- HELPFUL TIPS!
    
    new page: <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/> replace the x's with the file number and then the page number, should correspond with the file names in the sharepoint JPEG file folder
    headings: <head>HEADING IV.</head>
    subheadings: <head type="sub">less aggressive heading</head>
    linebreak: <lb/> use whenever there is a linebreak, usually common with subheadings or headings on the first page of a lecture
    paragraphs: <p></p> example: <p>all my awesome text, yippee</p>
    em dash: &#8212;
    italicized text: <hi rend="italic"></hi> example: <hi rend="italic">text that is italicized</hi>
    stupid words that are cut off at the end of a page: 
    
    <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice>
    
    
    
    -->

<pb facs="hta.010.001"/>
    
    <head>LECTURE VI.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, XII. PART OF VER. 3.</bibl><lb/>
    <hi rend="italic">And in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed.</hi></head>

    <p>Such were the words which were spoken to Abraham by the Lord. The tenour of the promises is no less important to us than to the children of Israel, who, as descendants of Abraham, considered themselves sole heirs of the promise. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q001" source="kjv">"We, by adoption," says the Apostle, "are become the children of the promise, and joint heirs with Christ of the kingdom of heaven."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q001" resp="#eds">Romans 8:15-17</bibl> If then, all the families of the earth are blessed in the seed of Abraham, it must be worth while for all of us to inquire with particular attention into every circumstance of Abraham's life and character, which the sacred historian has recorded. Nor can there be a stronger proof that such an inquiry was expected on the part of Moses, and, consequently, approved on that of Heaven, than the copiousness and minuteness of his narrative in all that regards this patriarch. We will, therefore, first inform
    
<pb facs="hta.010.002"/>    
    ourselves on the point of Abraham's genealogy. To the three sons of Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japhet, various parts of the ancient world were severally assigned either by mutual agreement or the express injunction of Noah. the descendents of Japhet seem to have spread themselves westward through Europe, or, in the words of Scripture, the isles of the Gentiles. We may here observe, that the distribution of Japhet's family is very briefly mentioned; the reason is obvious; they were not to act any very material part in the history of the Jews, for whose instruction and guidance Moses chiefly wrote, so long as that people retained any claim to the title of a nation; while the genealogy and future possessions of Ham, though accursed of his father, are detailed very much at lenght. We are presented with an account of many generations, and the names of several nations which they founded, and cities which they built, to the end that we might fully perceive the faithfullness of God's threats, as well as his promises; and know that the posterity of Ham were the Canaanite, the Jebusite, the Amorite, the Hivite, and the Phillistine, with many other equally idolatrous tribes, who nearly one thousand years after the sin of their undutiful progenitor, fell before the hand of the Lord by the sword of Joshua, David, and other appointed instruments of his will. To shem, as the <choice><reg>firstborn</reg><orig>first-
            
<pb facs="hta.010.003"/>
        born</orig></choice>, God gave for a season the privilege of his birthright. The eastern countries beyond the region of Ham were probably the first possessions; the beautiful plains of Shinar, through which the Tigris runs, comprehending the country of Eden, where Paradise had been situated. But the most valuable privilege of birthright was, that from Shem should in fact descend that favoured Being, to whom the promises of God were to be much more fully detailed, much more frequently repeated, and much more clearly explained, than they had ever before been&#8212;namely, Abraham, the father of the faithful. Moses, therefore, with the utmost precision, delivers an uninterrupted genealogy of nine generations, from Shem to Abraham. The consistency of the Lord is thus made manifest in dispensing upon Abraham and his seed, so long as they should be obedient, those blessings which he promised to Shem in consideration of his pious and dutiful conduct, in concealing the errors of the a father. Nor will it show the consistency of God less plainly, that to Japhet also it had been promises that he should be ENLARGED. His ulterior enlargement, it seems, was commenced as early even as the first intimation of Shem's immediate prosperity;&#8212;the enlargement and extension of Christianity among the western nations was predicted precisely at
    
<pb facs="hta.010.004"/>    
    the same amount as the previous election of the Jews; and the same design was afterwards plainly typified at least twice, even in the very families of the patriarchs, when Isaac was preferred to Ishmael, and Jacob to Esau.</p>
    <p>Before we proceed to detail the singular and important events which distinguished the life and conduct of Abraham, it may be right to remind ourselves, that they have been handed down to us for two principal purposes: the first is, to assure us that God from the beginning had determined on the salvation of mankind, by the sacrifice of a pure and sufficient victim: the second is, to teach us the inseperable union between obeying God's commandments and believing in his promises; in other words, the inseperable compact between good works and fervent faith, which was expected from the children of circumcision, and which will not be dispensed with in the better instructed children of the Gospel:therefore the obedience and the faith of Abraham are what we are to regard as chiefly contributive to our edification.</p>
    <p>The first test of obedience which was demanded of Abraham by the Lord was such as in those times must have been severer than we now perhaps are fully aware of. It was, to <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q002" source="kjv">"get him out of his country, and from his kindred, and from his father's house, unto a land which was
    
<pb facs="hta.010.005"/>   
        to be shown him."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q002" resp="#eds">Genesis 12:1</bibl>Such was the peremptory word of the Lord. Let is be observed, that when the command was given, it was not accompanied with any intimation where that land was to be, under what climate, of what quality, whether near or remote, friendly or hostile. As far as Abraham's feelings and knowledge were concerned, it was to him, as when the angel with the falming sword expelled his first parents from Paradise. The whole world was before him&#8212;exile seemed certain, repose or advantage very doubtful. And, as I before said, there were at that period of the world habits, customs, and feelings which made the seperation of a patriarchal family much more grievous than can well be understood in the present state of society. Better wer it, perhaps, for the virtue of society, if men did not so easily break the bonds of parental, filial, and fraternal affection. In proportion as men strip themselves of what they call the weakness of natural affection, it is to be feared that they depart from the love of all simplicity, consequently from the love of godliness and God; and whilst they proudly boast themselves of a conquest over prejudices, they in fact are, in the language of an Apostle, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q003" source="kjv">"searing their consciences with a red-hot iron."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q003" resp="#eds">1 Timothy 4:2</bibl> Let those who enjoy the blessing of domestic happiness, diffused liberally and revolving fithfully through the various parts of an extended
    
<pb facs="hta.010.006"/>    
    circle, estimate its value by recalling to mind that God proposed it as a sacrifice to Abraham, that he should get him out from his kindred and from his father's house.</p>





</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


