<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.027" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="jh">Harper, Jordan</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="project">hta.027</idno>
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-04"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

    <pb facs="hta.027.001"/>
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.002"/> <!-- one head with line breaks -->
    <head>TO
        THE REVEREND
        J.B.S. CARWITHEN, B.D.
        AND
        THE CONGREGATION ASSEMBLED
        AT
        THE OPENING OF FRIMLEY CHURCH.</head>
    
    <p>MY DEAR FRIENDS,</p>
    <p>THE following discourse is published, as it was delivered, at your request. It is very gratifying to me that the result of it has answered your expectations; and I have only to wish that my readers (if any read it) may partake of that liberal and indulgent feeling which animated those who heard it.</p>
    <p>With the sincerest prayer for your temporal
        and eternal welfare,</p>
    <p>I am,</p>
    <p>Your faithful and obliged Friend,</p>
    <p>H.T. AUSTEN.</p>
    <p>FARNHAM, October 31st, 1826.</p>

    <pb facs="hta.027.003"/>

    <p>IT has been justly observed by a very eloquent writer and a very pious man, that "where many think alike they must be right." The testimony of concurrent feelings is never to be lightly regarded. Therefore, if Revelation had not spoken so decisively on the subject, we might rest the cause of public worship on early and general usage&#8212;we might rest it on the immemorial practices of those Nations, who knowing not the true God, were in religious matters a law unto themselves. We are borne out in this by the voice of History&#8212;no penury of Religious rites, no paucity of places set apart for the periodical celebration of them, marks any Nation of whom we retain record or report. Scripture, the best authority, even on points of narrative, tells us that the great and
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.004"/>
        
        crying Sin of the elder times was not Atheism, but idolatry. The Caananite, adn every other Nation which fell before the armies of the living God may be cited as a proof. They worshipped they knew not what! They worshipped with rites absurd, gross, and cruel&#8212;but still they worshipped publicly, nationally.</p> 
    
    <p>with solemn ceremonies, and superstitious adherence to locality, they raised their idols in every grove and on every high hill. Not dissimilar the above was the disposition of the later Pagans. Rome at once the mistress of the world and the slave of superstition, was a city of temples, and even to this day there is scarcely an eminence along the shores of Greece on which the ruins of some majestic shrine do not prove, that to erect innumerable places of public worship, and to adorn them with every embellishment of sculpture, was a delight to Nations supereminent in arts and sciences</p>
    <p>It is evident at a disposition to public worship has been infused into man, by Him who fashioned the ear and planted the eye.</p>
    <p>This disposition hath been duly directed by the Word of Revelation. We, of the present day, are obeying God's declared Will when we set apart times and places for public <choice><reg>worship</reg><orig>wor-
        
    <pb facs="hta.027.005"/>
        
        ship</orig></choice>, as much as when we observe any one of the ten Commandments.</p>
    <p>When the Lord delivered Israel from captivity and eased his shoulders from making the pots, did He not enter into an everlasting Covenant with him ordered in all things? Did He not instruct his Prophet Moses to build him a Tabernacle, a Tabernacle for the congregation? Did He not ordain his servant Aaron to a perpetual priesthood? Think ye, my brethren, that so large a portion of the Pentateuch would have been devoted to a minute detail of the Jewish Ritual, the Jewish Priesthood, the Jewish Sanctuary, its structure, ornaments and utensils? Would it have been recorded, or would it have been ordained that the Cloud of the Lord should rest on this Tabernacle, overshadowing it, or disclosing it to open view according as Israel was to journey or to rest? Would all this have been so precisely written, so faithfully preserved, had it not been meant for the instruction of those who were yet for to come? That we might remember the works of the Lord, his statutes and ordinances, calling to mind that a complete religious Establishment, a separated Priesthood, an undeviating Ritual, a consecrated Tabernacle were prescribed by God himself&#8212;
        
    <pb facs="hta.027.006"/>
        
        prescribed to that Nation which he called peculiarly his own, which he selected for the preservation of his oracles and the fulfilment of his prophecies; that he made them an Ecclesiastical state before he made them a territorial nation, and gave them statutes and judgements to regulate their worship and raise their united voices to Heaven, before he permitted them to occupy one cubit of their earthly inheritance. Is it not evident that, although Heaven be his throne and Earth his footstool, although He be <hi rend="italic">in</hi> all, and <hi rend="italic">through</hi> all, and <hi rend="italic">above</hi> all&#8212;yet Man is to come into his courts, and to praise Him in the Sanctuary? Altho' it may appear superfluous to argue further on the propriety, expedience, and duty of public worship, and consequently on the necessity of providing fit places for its performance, yet on the present occasion I will pursue the subject a little farther&#8212;and I do so, being fully persuaded that to those who are not very conversant with their Bible, it is always beneficial to be presented with strong and lively instances of God's dealings with Man of old, while those, who are most conversant with their Bible, feel renewed and increasing satisfaction from every reference to such testimonies. Scripture is the strong hold to which we should
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.007"/>
        
        alway resort. Scripture will teach us that although God, being a spirit must be worshiped in spirit and in truth, yet nevertheless by his appointment, the realities of Heaven must be figured on Earth by Earthly forms; and that all things must be done decently and in order, how much so ever Unbelief may openly mock our devotion: how much so ever Schism, that worm which never dies, may secretly calumniate and decry, our most Apostolic solemnities.</p>
    <p>When the Jews were established in the promised land, the same strict attention to the formalities of public worship continued to be enforced under the same Divine authority.&#8212;David, a man most after God's own heart, by which expression we are to understand that his thoughts and affections were turned to God more uniformly and more ardently than those of other men, David, acting under the influence of Inspiration, has placed on everlasting record his pious design of building a house for the Lord. The same heavenly interposition which suspended tbe execution of this design on the part of David, directed its accomplishment under Solomon his son. It was specially reserved for the most powerful, magnificent, prosperous and enlightened Monarch of the
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.008"/>
    
        Jewish Race, to build a Habitation for the Mighty God of Jacob. Here we are plainly taught, that whenever a Nation is raised to peculiar prosperity, after peculiar struggles, it is bound to display its gratitude to its defender and presenter, by works of religious zeal and pious munificence. It would exceed the limits of my discourse were I to enlarge in description of the first Temple, though in many respects not inapplicable to the cause which I am advocating, yet I cannot entirely pass over some c1rcumstances of its dedication. They are impressively recorded in the Book of Kings and Chronicles. After appropriate sacrifices and a solemn address from the lips of Solomon, never surpassed by human piety or eloquence, the approbation and acceptance of the Almighty is recorded in these words, "when Solomon had made an end of praying, the fire came down from Heaven, and consumed the Burnt Offerings and the Sacrifices; and the glory of the Lord filled the house." <!--BIBLE VERSE--></p>
    <p>The glory of Solomons Temple, my brethren, hath long been done away; twice since the building of it, has the house of Judah been led into captivity; twice has Jerusalem been laid even with the dust, and twice the Beauty of Holiness become a prey to its enemies.
                
    <pb facs="hta.027.009"/>
    
        But a Mightier than Solomon hath made all things new! He hath led Captivity Captive, He hath raised up a Spiritual and Universal Church, built on the foundation of the Prophets and Apostles, of which He, Jesus Christ himself, is the Chief Corner Stone. "The Glory of the Lord filled the Temple of Solomon so that the Priests could not see to minister." <!-- BIBLE VERSE --> That house, being made with hands, hath passed away, but the Glory of the Lord remaineth! It remaineth in every Christian Church, and so filleth it that thereby <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> the Priest seeth clearly to minister. The knowledge of the Lord Jesus who is made unto us both the wisdom and the power of God, maketh our ministration rather glorious. The Sacrifices and Burnt Offerings in Solomon's Temple were consumed uy material fire from Heaven. Sacrifices and Burnt Offerings from us God hath not required, therefore of material flame have we no need. One and but one imperishable Sacrifice hath been made for us&#8212;a Sacrifice not consumed, over which no element could have dominon&#8212;but for us and our sanctification celestial fire hath descended. The fire of the Holy Spirit lighted on the heads of the Apostles, and was received into their hearts. By this penetrating agency were their tongues
           
    <pb facs="hta.027.010"/>
    
        loosed to preach to all nations.&#8212;By this were their understandings opened to understand, and their zeal directed to transmit to faithful witnesses the Word of God; which is our firm assurance of eternal life, and which shall flourish and spread among our posterities, and bnng forth fruit as long as the Sun and Moon endureth.</p>
    <p>Greatly should we disparage the power and the love of our blessed Lord, were we to suppose that the highest influences of the Holy Spirit were confined to the day of Pentecost, or circumscribed by the chamber where the Apostles were assembled. As surely as the Spirit of God moved on the face of the waters at the hour of Creation, so surely ever since the hour of Redemption, when Christ ascended into the holy of holies, the same spirit hath delighted to dwell among Men, and to make his sanctuary in their hearts.</p>
    <p>Every one who hath been baptized with water into the name of Jesus, may be thus baptized with fire. His own fervent prayers put up in faith, will excite the sanctifying flame, an attract the promised comforter. Every one baptized into the name of Christ, who devoutly reads, or devoutly listens to the word of God&#8212;every one who thus with all his
        
    <pb facs="hta.027.011"/>   
        
    heart, and all his soul, and all his strength searches the Scriptures, will find that these things are so; and that although we may appear to the worldly-minded as those who mock, yet we really speak the words of soberness and truth.</p>
    <p>Are then your minds set upon Righteousness O ye Congregation? Have ye remembered that this is the House of Prayer, to day the accepted time? If ye have, what need we any further witness? any further witness than your own hearts? Every one amongst you must feel an increase of warmth and light, of that warmth and light which the Holy Spirit sheds abroad to instruct and to comfort&#8212;to point out the way, and send you on your way rejoicing. Thus doth the Glory of the Lord fill every Christian Church; and thus are constantly fulfilled, those words which the Lord of Glory hath spoken: "When two or three are gathered together in my name, there will I be in tl1e midst of them."<!-- BIBLE VERSE --> St. Paul certainly entertained very sublime and spiritual views of his Master's Religion; yet no one more peremptorily than St. Paul, enjoins attendance on public worship, as the test of a Christian's sincerity and the support of a Christian's faith. How does he exhort the Hebrews to hold fast the profession of their faith without wavering? By not forsaking the
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.012"/>
    
    assembling of themselves together. The Apostle gave this charge when Christians could not perform these duties without great personal danger; yet still the Apostle makes his rule absolute and inclusive&#8212;"Not forsaking the assembling of ourselves together as the manner of some is." <!-- BIBLE VERSE -->These latter very probably neglected or deserted the public worship of their Lord for fear of persecution, still professing their faith. But the Apostle to whom through the spirit their hearts were open, does not therefore hold them excused! He makes no reservation! He had not so learned Christ nor would he teach him so. How then applies this Scripture to us? We cannot be deterred from assembling ourselves together by any fear of persecution. On the contrary it is safe, decent, respectable (I speak as a Man) for every person in these realms to join in public worship. Quite inexcusable therefore are we, my brethren and wantonly trifling with the appointed means of Grace, if we forsake the assembling of ourselves together as, alas! the manner of some is. May the number of such truly blind, self-destroying, yet still most pitiable outcasts, be lessened every Sabbath Day! and as often as we do assemble ourselves together, let us never forsake them in our prayers! Though they
        
    <pb facs="hta.027.013"/>  
     
     pray not for themselves, let us pray for them; though they may hold us in derision, still are they greater enemies to themselves than to us. Let us pray for them that the spirit of a right mind be not utterly taken from them&#8212;that the mercy of God be not clean removed out of their sight, but that they may be yet brought home with many other wanderers to the Flock of Christ. Every one of us who can pray thus heartily, thus wisely&#8212;every one of us who would rejoice to hear encreasing members say, "Let us go into the House of the Lord" <!-- BIBLE VERSE -->will gladly co-operate, according to our several abilities in the cause which I am now pleading. It is a cause which has received the sanction of the Legislature and the support of our Rules and therein our Senators have shewed their wisdom, and our Rulers their righteousness.</p>
    <p>It must often have occured to all of us, (too often it cannot) that no Nation has ever been more favored by Providence than ourselves within the last twenty years; we had fightings without and fears within; we were hemmed about with enemies, even those who had been our familiar friends, and if the Lord himself had not been on our side, it had not failed but they had swallowed us up quick. But the
        
    <pb facs="hta.027.014"/>       
        
        Lord had a favor unto us, and why? Not for any merits of our own&#8212;No, That we dare not say! It was that the Lord selected us as instruments of Righteousness. He hath set our City on a Hill, to be a light to those who sit in darkness. He hath scattered our enemies, He hath shewn us his wonders in the deep that we may make known his ways on earth, his saving health unto all nations.</p>
    <p>This is the journey on which he hath sent us! This the message he hath bidden us deliver. This should be the brightest trophy of our victorious arms. This the richest export of our boundless commerce.</p>
    <p>Thus may we make the world our willing debtors, by the imperishable loan of Religious instruction!</p>
    <p>Let us thank God then, that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are citizens of that Country, here the wise liberality of the Government has been so cheerfully followed up by the pious benevolence of Individuals, for the purpose of encreasing the number and capacity of Churches and Chapels throughout these realms. Were we to be silent to-day on such a subject, the very stone out of the wall would cry out against us.</p>
    <p>After duly inspecting the edifice in which we are now gathered together, every candid
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.015"/>
        
        person must admit that it is most happily adapted to the purpose designed. In point of commodiousness, symmetry, and arrangement within, it is a model which most officiating ministers have reason to wish were imitated in their respective Churches; and of which the Inhabitants of this parish can duly appreciate the merit, only by comparing it with the Churches in the Neighborhood. The simple elegance of its exterior, does credit to the taste of those who planned and executed it.</p>
    <p>The former Church was in every respect the reverse of that which is now erected&#8212;of mean construction&#8212;of materials so unsubstantial that they could not be calculated at more than £70 in part of the present Church&#8212;and incapable of containing more than 200 persons; whereas the New Church will contain 600 sittings, of which 400 are free.</p>
    <p>As the population of Frimley Parish amounts to about 1300 persons, no one can look on this Church as unnecessarily large; and when the constant increase of population be considered; he who can suppose that there will long be any room to spare here, must either doubt the truth of prophecy which uniformly declares that all shall be brought to a knowledge of God, or must be very indifferent to
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.016"/> <!-- lots of obscured text --><!-- use SUPPLIED tag from sermon recording -->
    
   the vigilance and activity with which Dissenters of every description, erect their conventicles wherever the Established Church is slow or meagre in furnishing accommodation for its flock: Look round on the number and size of these conventicles, and then tell us, do you suppose that the planners and promoters of them, when they laid the first stone, were anxious to ascertain what might be the smallest possible number of their congregation? Far from it. To do them justice, they are wiser in their generation. Then let us put away all such frigid <!-- idk --> calculation, all such unrighteous economy and be assured that if we provide the opportunity, God will give the increase. If we make ready the feast and set it in a large room, God will furnish it with guests.</p>
    <p>To enact <!-- idk --> this obvious and most desirable improvement, an expenditure of £2,300 has been incurred; in aid of which £400 has been supplied by the Society, &amp;c. for building and enlarging Churches and Chapels, and about £700 more by private benevolence</p>
    <p>Probably some very liberal contributors are among those to whom I am making this statement, and I am sure it would be painful to them were I to distinguish them by name. They seek not the praise of Men; they have
    
   <pb facs="hta.027.017"/>
    
    a far more exceeding reward in witnessing that this their labor of love has not been in vain. But I feel it my duty to state that from each of the Members who represent this County in Parliament, a donation of £50 has been received. May their example spread far and wide! Those men are fittest to legislate for us, who thus provoke us to good works. We shall never be inclined to withold from Cæsar <!-- weird combined ae symbol? -->the things that are Cæsar's, so long as our Senators thus encourage us to give unto God the things that are God's.</p>
    <p>There is also another donation of £50 which must not be passed over in silence. It is a gift receiving double value from the hand that gives it; yet while it demands our loyal gratitude, still it can excite no sensation of surprise. The high personage to whom I allude, has long obtained the tribute of respect greater than his rank can bestow, by standing forth the princely patron of every patriotic and religious work.</p>
    <p>Still there remains to be provided the sum of £1,200, a very heavy sum for the resources and means of this parish. As the minister and steward of the mercies of Christ I lay this statemeut before you: I ask you in His name to contribute to the building of His house;
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.018"/> <!-- lots of obscured text -->
    
    Whatever you contribute is lent to the Lord, and when He cometh, you shall receive your own with usury.</p>
    <p>Again must I look round on this edifice, and again wish it good luck in the name of the Lord. How honorable would it be to the possesssors of opulence and influence in their respective districts, if every Church in this Diocese were rendered half as commodious! However highly they may now think of their own judgement in the accumulation or the expenditure of their substance; however little they may now brook the remonstrance, or attend to the recommendations of God's Minister on this subject; the moment will come, when all of their speculations and investments, none will afford to their anxious recollections, one-tenth part of the satisfaction which will be felt in the end of his life, and at the end of his <!-- obscured --> by the poorest amongst you, who flings <!-- obscured --> day, his mite into the Treasury of God.</p>
    <p>I have risen up among you, my Friends, purposing to speak none other things than what ye must acknowledge to be true. In this confidence have I come unto you: and being thus minded could I use lightness? could I keep back <!-- obscured --> thing from such a congregation
    
    <pb facs="hta.027.019"/>
    
    which it was <hi rend="italic">my</hi> duty to say or <hi rend="italic">theirs</hi> to hear? I have not endeavored to catch you with enticing speech. Knowing the goodness of my cause and my own infirmity, I have only covenanted with myself that my words should not be yea and nay. Had I the tongue of an Apostle or of Angels I could effect nothing, but by the preventing Grace of God working in your hearts. I trust that it is working in you, both to will, and to do; that it is leading you, thankfully to accept the gracious conditions of the text&#8212;"To make the Lord a Sanctuary, that he may dwell among you."</p>
    
    <head type="sub">FINIS.</head> <!-- should this be a subhead? -->
    
    
    
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


