<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.005" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">Lecture I</title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="jh">Harper, Jordan</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="project">hta.005</idno>
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-02"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<pb facs="hta.005.001"/>

    <head>LECTURES,<lb/>
        &amp;c.</head>
        <head type="sub">LECTURE I.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, I. I.</bibl>
        <hi rend="italic">In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth.</hi></head>
        
    <p>HE who studies history aright, makes himself wise by the experience of others; and whosoever devotes a due portion of his researches to the authentic history of the creation, may make himself thereby wise to everlasting salvation. The object of such study is to ascertain the difference between Christianity and any other religion. Now the difference between Christianity and all other religions, as an eminent divine has correctly stated, is, that the latter are the result of human invention, whilst the former rests on revelation alone. Again, the mark which, we humbly trust, may be said to distinguish a reformed Christianity, is, that its professors and disciples have been careful and correct in <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.005.002"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice> the undoubted word of God, and separating it from those precepts, principles, and institutions (however recommended by antiquity, or endeared by custom), which have proceeded from the well-meant but superstitious piety of man, and are unconsecrated by any test of inspiration.</p>
    <p>Thanks to the learning, the piety, and the fortitude of our predecessors in the Church, we have liberal access to genuine and authenticated versions of Holy Writ. It is a privilege of which we may boast&#8212;it is a privilege, also, which may work our shame and condemnation, if we do not avail ourselves of it. Our Lord said unto the perverse Jews, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q001" source="kjv">"Verily, if ye were blind, ye should have no sin; but now ye say, We see; therefore your sin remaineth."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q001" resp="#eds">John 9:41</bibl> So, in like manner, had it not pleased God to accord unto us the means of unlimited instruction in all that appertains to salvation, we should have shared in the excuse, by sharing in the ignorance which envelops many a people calling itself Christian. But now are we inexcusable, my beloved friends, if we refuse to drink the living waters of truth at their purest source. Of all studies, that of the Scriptures will be found most delightful, if judged of by the effects produced on the hearts, tempers, understandings, and morals of those who persevere

    <pb facs="hta.005.003"/>
    
    in it to the end. As our Saviour saith to the Samaritan woman, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q002" source="kjv">"Whosoever shall drink of the water which I shall give him, shall never thirst."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q002" resp="#eds">John 4:14</bibl> But to participate in such a blessing, we must drink deeply and often,&#8212;nothing doubting but that God doth favourably regard the researches of all those who thirst after righteousness, and that his Spirit is ever present like the rod of Moses to smite the stony rock, and make water-springs of the dry ground.</p>
    <p>From a variety of causes unnecessary for me now to expatiate on, it needs must be that a certain number here present have been cut off from many opportunities of becoming intimately acquainted with their Bible, and have perhaps insensibly ceased to regret, that such opportunities have not more frequently occurred.&#8212;<quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q003" source="kjv">"Awake thou that sleepest, and Christ shall give thee light."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q003" resp="#eds">Ephesians 5:14</bibl> It is my ardent prayer to Heaven that all such should know, while it is yet day, the things which make for their peace; it is my duty to beseech them, that they will permit me in all humility to minister unto them in the bonds of the Gospel. It is my confident belief, that if we sincerely labour together in the study of divine truth, our labour will not be in vain in the Lord, but that we shall redeem the time.</p>
    
    <pb facs="hta.005.004"/>
    
    <p>Considering how and where we are now gathered together, it seemeth to me, my Christian friends, that we come more especially under that appellation, with which St. Peter, in his Epistle general, addresses the converts of his day. He reminds them that they are pilgrims and sojourners, and he exhorts them to prepare for heaven, because here they have no abiding place. On earth, no doubt, every man is a pilgrim and a sojourner: though he may build, and occupy, and plant vineyards, and join field to field, and call the land after his own name, yet we know full well, and we acknowledge full readily (when we pause for the better purpose of meditation), that the Lord is no respecter of persons; that neither clime, nor nation, nor kindred, availeth any thing in his sight; that if we uttermost parts of the earth, we cannot flee from our conscience; and that they who rest under the shadow of the Almighty are always at home. Still, however, it may not be useless to consider ourselves, in a peculiar manner, pilgrims and sojourners; if by such reflection on our immediate position, we be induced to entwine the religious rites and ordinances of our beloved country more closely about our hearts, and so prepare ourselves, during a transient separation from many whom we love, as to secure a perpetual re-union with them hereafter in a better
        
    <pb facs="hta.005.005"/>
   
   country, a city not made with hands. It is my design, in the plainest manner possible, to set before you a brief and general view of the Scriptures; that you may be enabled to see what connexion subsists between the creation, the fall, the redemption of man; between prophecy, promise, and miracle; between the justice and the mercy of God.</p>
    <p><quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q004" source="kjv">"In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q004" resp="#eds">Genesis 1:1</bibl>&#8212;I have selected for my text the very first words of our common Bible. If any words be familiar to your ears, I must presume these to be so. They commence the book of Genesis: the book is so called, because it treats principally of the creation of the world, with all that therein is, and the earlier generations of the human race, with a particular account of that family which was set apart from the beginning, to preserve the true faith, receive the first covenant of God, and in whose seed all the nations of the earth were to be blessed.</p>
    <p>The book of Genesis, as well as the four books immediately succeeding it, in the usual arrangement, namely, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy, were written by Moses, and put together in their present form (with a very few additions) by Samuel. Moses was that prophet whom God raised up about 2500
    
        <pb facs="hta.005.006"/>
        
        years after the creation, for the purpose of delivering the chosen people of Israel from their bondage in Egypt, and conducting them back to the land which had been promised to their forefathers. To Moses was vouchsafed a degree of access to the Lord of Hosts, and a portion of inspiration, beyond any other prophet. He was, in his generation, a type and representative of our Saviour, who was to deliver all the chosen people of God, whether Jew or Gentile, from the bondage of sin, and conduct them back to a heavenly kingdom prepared from the foundations of the world. In reminding ourselves that we have the authority of Moses for the authenticity and inspiration of these earlier portions of Scripture, we cannot but be satisfied that their contents are as important and as essential as they are true. God, who never leaves himself without a witness, has, in this instance, closed the mouth of scepticism, by selecting as the historian of creation and all its mysteries, that only one of his servants to whom he had spoken face to face, and to whom he had delivered the tables of the commandments written with his own hand. We must, therefore, consider the Mosaic account of ancient times, not only as entitled to our respect, but as being in fact dictated by the Spirit of God, and preserved by his providence, so that we might possess one perfect history of his dealings with mankind.
    
        <pb facs="hta.005.007"/>
        
        Remember, therefore, that when you open your Bibles, you open the volume of the book of the Lord. And when you read his written word, may his Spirit rest upon you! may you read, mark, learn, and inwardly digest it, to the comfort of your own souls!</p>
    <p><quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q005" source="kjv">"In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q005" resp="#eds">Genesis 1:1</bibl>&#8212;The expression is magnificent and simple. It is also truly philosophical, and rationally pious. It lays down as a primary article, the existence of an Almighty Being, and it solves at once all the wonders and difficulties of creation, by describing it as the work of his hands. It leads us directly to the root of all natural religion.</p>
    <p>In the above expression we have a representation of God the Creator in the unity of the Father; but, as if to prepare us for the future revelation of the Trinity, we meet in the 2d verse with this remarkable expression: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q006" source="kjv">"And the <hi rend="italic">Spirit of God</hi> moved upon the face of the waters."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q006" resp="#eds">Genesis 1:2</bibl> We cannot hereby but understand that the Holy Spirit, to whom we address ourselves as to the third Personage in the Trinity, was an original mover in the creative work, as surely as he is a final operator in our ultimate sanctification. I would on no account have you overlook these minute and early intimations
        
        <pb facs="hta.005.008"/>
     
     of the truth of that faith which we are to profess agreeably to the Articles of our reformed Church. The whole of the first chapter of Genesis is devoted to a short but incomparable and satisfactory account of the creation, which God completed in six days. The sixth or last day of creation, was distinguished from those which preceded it, by the creation of man. What importance was annexed by God to this his last work, and for what high designs man was originally destined, we shall best understand, by referring to the 26th verse of this chapter: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q007" source="kjv">"And God said, Let <hi rend="italic">us</hi> make man in our image, after our likeness."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q007" resp="#eds">Genesis 1:26</bibl></p>
    <p>The above most extraordinary and awful intimation of heavenly will, can be only understood in this way. The Father must be considered as addressing himself to our Lord Jesus Christ, and as thus exhibiting and declaring the equal Godhead of the Son, by associating him in that counsel which decided the formation and the form of man. Hence, we naturally concur in the sentiment and declaration both of St. John and St. Paul, respecting the eternal existence of our Lord and Saviour. Well might the former say, "In the beginning was the Word&#8212;by him were all things made, and without him was not any thing made that was made." St. John does but enlarge on what Moses had declared.
    
        <pb facs="hta.005.009"/>
    
    Well might St. Paul remind the Hebrews that God had appointed his Son heir of all things, that by him he had made the worlds, that in him were revealed the brightness of his glory and the express image of his person. In this very image was man originally created&#8212;so that when, in after-times, the Son of God became incarnate, well might it be said, that he came unto his own; and in all things he was made like unto us, sin only excepted.</p>
    <p>God created man in his own image; and I then, as a farther distinction, he breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and there on man became a living soul. It is worthy of our notice, that the divine historian applies this cause of existence to man alone. He tells us, that God formed all the various tribes of animated matter, all that swim, or creep, or walk, or fly; that he assigned them their respective elements, and allotted them their several states; that all were perfect in their degree; but from the first it was man only that God blessed, it was to man only that a soul was imparted. Let, therefore, the materialist remember, that he contends against the most ancient authority of learning, when he contends that man has not a soul distinct from that principle of life which he enjoys in common with the brutes that perish.</p>
    
     <pb facs="hta.005.010"/>
    
    <p>Having given a comprehensive detail of creation, the sacred historian in the next place calls our attention to that which may with propriety be called the first miracle as regarding man; I mean the mode in which it pleased God to form a help meet for him. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q008" source="kjv">"And the Lord God caused a deep sleep to fall upon Adam, and he slept, and he took one of his ribs, and closed up the flesh thereof. And the rib which the Lord God had taken from man, made he a woman, and brought her unto the man."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q008" resp="#eds">Genesis 2:21-23</bibl> I am aware that the above mysterious origin of woman has often been a subject of groundless contempt and impertinent ridicule to those who measure the operations of God's hand by the narrowness of their own vulgar imaginations. But what is there in it deserving of ridicule or mockery? Shall the thing made say unto its maker, I will not believe that such or such was the fashion, or the manner, or the source of my formation? It was, doubtless, exactly as easy for God to have made woman, like man, out of the dust of the earth; but it was not easier. Nor would such a mode of creation have been less wondrous than the one detailed by Moses. It is beyond the province of reason to pronounce on the comparative possibility of things: we therefore are not justified in objecting to the Mosaic account of female formation, on any ground of its being
    
      <pb facs="hta.005.011"/>
    
    more extraordinary than that of man. Now, strip it of that which our hasty mode of judgment pronounces extraordinary, and there is no reason for not giving as implicit credit to it as to any other part of the preceding chapters.</p>
    <p>To the truly attentive and sober-minded readers of Scripture, it must occur that Moses, whose interest it was to persuade those for whose instruction he wrote, would never, from his own invention, or any other authority short of divine, have made a statement so likely to inspire doubt and disbelief in the minds of the Jews, whom he knew to be a perverse and stiffnecked people. As neither the glory, nor profit, nor influence of Moses could have induced him to assert such a gratuitous and dangerous falsehood, I must ever consider that his veracity on the above point is sufficiently established by the very singularity of the fact. It could not have entered into the imagination of man to invent such an occurrence, much less into the mind of one, who, like Moses, was free from all vulgar and ignorant superstition, being deeply versed in all the knowledge of the Egyptians. But we need go no further for a most satisfactory explanation of this seeming mystery, than to the words of the succeeding verse; <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q009" source="kjv">"Therefore shall a man leave his father and his
    
      <pb facs="hta.005.012"/>
    
    mother, and shall cleave unto his wife; and they two shall be one flesh."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q009" resp="#eds">Genesis 2:24</bibl> Such was the everlasting prediction of Adam, a prophecy which, though poured forth in the hour of original innocence, still in its fulfilment has survived all other wrecks of human happiness.</p>
    <p>On such deep foundations has it pleased God in his mercy to raise the structure of connubial felicity. With what profound respect ought man to regard this earliest prediction of his forefather! How greatly careful ought he to be, that he doth not wrest this remnant of paradise to his own destruction! Thus have the oldest records of the world on divine authority declared, that the state of wedlock, if rightly understood, shall be at once the source, the trial, and the reward of human virtue on the sphere of human action. That wedlock was destined to exercise our constancy and our fidelity, cannot be doubted; nor can it be contradicted, that its enjoyments are strictly proportionate to the purity with which these virtues are exercised. However, in darker times, and under an imperfect law, polygamy might have been permitted; however Moses, on account of the hardness of their hearts might have conceded to the Jews too wide a latitude of divorce; be ye, my Christian friends, assured that such a mistaken liberty is a disgrace to
    
      <pb facs="hta.005.013"/>
    
    the profession of a Christian, poison to the morals of a people, and ruin to the happiness of individuals. Tell me only, how the duties of marriage are understood and practised in any civilized nation; and I will tell you what respect it enjoys abroad, and what pledge it possesses for peace and prosperity at home. They, and they alone, who conscientiously act up to the vows of a husband and a wife, can act up to the character of good. parents, can rear up their sons and daughters like the polished corners of the temple, can bequeath them as a legacy useful to their country, and an offering acceptable to God. To such a husband and to such a wife, may we apply the encouraging promise of the Psalmist: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.005.q010" source="kjv">"O well is thee, and happy shalt thou be: thou shalt see thy children's children, and peace upon Israel."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.005.q010" resp="#eds">Psalm 128:5-6</bibl></p>
    
    
    
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


