<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.021" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="hb">Borrell, Hannah</name> <!-- if you are not Jordan Harper, change to your initials and name -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
    <idno type="project">hta.021</idno> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-07"><name sameAs="#hb"/> transcribed and encoded</change> <!-- replace with correct name and date -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<!-- transcribe lecture here -->
    <!-- HELPFUL TIPS!
    
    new page: <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/> replace the x's with the file number and then the page number, should correspond with the file names in the sharepoint JPEG file folder
    headings: <head>HEADING IV.</head>
    subheadings: <head type="sub">less aggressive heading</head>
    linebreak: <lb/> use whenever there is a linebreak, usually common with subheadings or headings on the first page of a lecture
    paragraphs: <p></p> example: <p>all my awesome text, yippee</p>
    em dash: &#8212;
    italicized text: <hi rend="italic"></hi> example: <hi rend="italic">text that is italicized</hi>
    stupid words that are cut off at the end of a page: 
    
    <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice>
    
    
    
    -->

<pb facs="hta.021.001"/>
    
    <head>LECTURE XVII.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, XXXVII. PART OF VER 1.</bibl><lb/>
        <hi rend="italic"></hi>And Jacob dwelt in the land wherin his father was a stranger.</head>

    <p>I concluded my last observations on the conduct and history of Jacob, with mentioning the amicable meeting between him and his brother Esau, not only after a seperation of twenty years which had been caused by the deadly anger and revengeful menaces of the elder against his younger brother. The joy which is felt in heaven over one sinner who repenteth, is most strongly dwelt on in the New Testament. The language of our Saviour was, on all occasions, the language of reconciliation. It was in perfect unison with the mighty purposes of Him who descended upon earth, that he might reconcile man to God. There cannot, therefore, be a stronger evidence adduced of the analogy and connexion subsisting between the Old and New Testament, than the similarity of sentiment pervading them.</p>
    
<pb facs="hta.021.002"/>    
    <p>Moses, who was the temporal saviour of the Jews, gives striking proof of his being the type of Christ on sundry occasions, but on none more strikingly than when he dwells with persuasiave and pathetic minuteness on all the circumstances of fraternal reconciliation. It was a very necessary lesson to the Jews in his day; and had they learnt from it to think somewhat less highly of themselves nationally, had they called to mind that they were orignally seperated from other nations, merely to do the will of God, and not to possess his favour by any right of their own, they might upon such becoming humility have engrafted a teachableness which would have prevented Jerusalem from becoming a heap of stones. For the pride which was their ruin, the Jews had no excuse nor model in the conduct of either Abraham, Isaac, or Jacob, favoured as these patriarchs were by sundry direct communications with God. The humility, forbearance, and conciliatory disposition of Jacob shine forth on every occasion, showing that the moral law of Christ was ever written in the heart of the faithful, and that they wlaked in the promise of a better law.</p>
    <p>ALthough Jacob had so lately received miraculous proof of God's being about his path, yet he in no degree departed from that soothing and
    
<pb facs="hta.021.003"/>    
    pacific line of conduct on which he had resolved before the vision at Peniel. He took of that which came to his hand, a present for Esau his brother. By the expression of taking <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q002" source="kjv">"that which came to his hand,"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q001" resp="#eds">Genesis 32:13</bibl> we are to understand that he made no reserve for himself of that which might be superior in quality: he did as became a brother. This present was, in fact, a noble one, consisting of <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q003" source="kjv">"two hundred she goats and twenty he goats, two hundred ewes and twenty rams, thirty milch camels with their colts, forty kine and ten bulls, twenty she asses and ten foals."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q003" resp="#eds">Genesis 32:13</bibl> That Jacob, who had passed over the brook <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q004" source="kjv">"with his staff only,"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q004" resp="#eds">Genesis 13:10</bibl> when he fled from Esau's anger, should he be able to set apart so magnificent a present without material prejudice to himself, and already numberous family, is an undeniable evidence that the hand of God had been with him, and converted his servitude under Laban into an ample inheritance. That the present was such as exceeded all expectation, we find from Esau's inquiry; for he said, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q005" source="kjv">"What meanest thou by all this drove which I met?"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q005" resp="#eds">Genesis 33:8</bibl> Jacob's reply was so simple, so ready, so warm, and so submissive, that it was accounted by his brother as more valuable than all the drove which he had met: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q006" source="kjv">"These are to find grace in the sight of my lord."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q006" resp="#eds">Genesis 33:8</bibl>&#8212;The expression of finding grace in the sight of Esau was of itself an acknowledgement
    
<pb facs="hta.021.004"/>    
    of his own personal inferiority, and the appellation of lord was conclusive on the matter. He was ready to pay that duty, which, in the patriarchal times, was due from a younger to an elder brother. Here was no assumption of his birthright in the eyes of men, from which we must understand that it related not to any heirship on earth as regarding Isaac's wealth, but referred to the promises of God, and the genealogy of the Messiah. Jacob, in this instance, affords an excellent lesson to those who give way to spiritual pride&#8212;of all pride most incurable, and most irrational; for, if any one giveth himself out to be great in the eyes of the Lord, he cometh directly under that sentence of our Lord Jesus Christ, which says, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q007" source="kjv">"Whosoever receiveth not the kingdom of heaven as a little cild, shall by no means enter therein."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q007" resp="#eds">Mark 10:15</bibl></p>
    <p>No doubt the whole meeting between Esau and Jacob was intended as a trial of the latter's humility. He humbled himself, and was, therfore, exalted. Modesty and resignation unlock the closest heart, and liberality is the most certain mode of eliciting a liberal return. Esau said, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q008" source="kjv">"I have enough, my brother; keep hat thou hast unto thyself."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q008" resp="#eds">Genesis 33:9</bibl>&#8212;The termination of this generous contest is worthy our notice and recollection. A renewed remonstrance on Jacob's part that his present might be received, 
        
<pb facs="hta.021.005"/>       
    was decisive, to the credit of both parties, and the instruction of all who have ears to hear. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q009" source="kjv">"Take, I pray thee, my blessing, that is brought, because God hath dealt graciously with me, and because I have enough."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q009" resp="#eds">Genesis 33:11</bibl>&#8212;As it now assumed a more solemn character, and became, as it were, an offering of thankfulness to that Providence which had so wonderfully preserved and enriched the one, converted the heart of the other, and brought both face to face, Esau no longer declines setting this seal upon the compact of friendly intercourse and renewed affection; the more so, asa by the latter words he fully understood that Jacob would suffer no inconvenience; for the words, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.021.q010" source="kjv">"I have enough,"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.021.q010" resp="#eds">Genesis 33:9</bibl> mean, in the original, I have all things, or <hi rend="italic">abundance.</hi> Therefore Esau accepted the present.</p>
    <p></p>







</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


