<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.026" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="jh">Harper, Jordan</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="project">hta.026</idno>
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-04"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>

<div type="sermon">

    <pb facs="hta.026.001"/>

    <head>A SERMON,<lb/>
    PREACHED AT BASINGSTOKE,<lb/>
    AT<lb/>
    THE VISITATION<lb/>
    OF THE<lb/>
    <hi rend="italic">Venerable Archdeacon of Winchester,</hi><lb/>
    MAY 24, 1821.<lb/>
    PUBLISHED AT THE REQUEST OF THE ARCHDEACON.<lb/>
    BY THE<lb/>
    Rev. HENRY THOMAS AUSTEN, A.M.<lb/>
    RECTOR OF STEVENTON.<lb/>
    WINCHESTER<lb/>
    PRINTED AND SOLD BY JACOB AND JOHNSON.<lb/>
    <hi rend="italic">At their County Newspaper Office, High Street,</hi><lb/>
    <unclear><!-- can't transcribe --></unclear>
    </head>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.002"/>
    
    <head type="sub">ST. JOHN, c: x. <hi rend="italic">Part of 16th Verse.</hi></head>
    <head><ref target="#hta.026.n01"></ref>THERE SHALL BE ONE FOLD AND ONE SHEPHERD.</head>
    
    <p>PROPHECY has never opened to the eye of Faith a more magnificent prospect of things to come than that which the words of our Text authorise and enjoin us to contemplate. Infidelity, Schism, and Dissension, must decrease&#8212;Communion of Doctrine, Creed, and Worship, must increase, until the knowledge of the Lord shall cover the Earth, and the Peace of God keep all hearts and minds. In the midst of present perplexity it is an inestimable consolation to know that the words of our Saviour must be fulfilled&#8212;that, sooner or later, confliction of <choice><reg>religious</reg><orig>reli-

     <note xml:id="hta.026.n01">Appendix, Note A.</note>  

    <pb facs="hta.026.003"/>
            
    gious</orig></choice> opinions must cease throughout all the world. This is a consolation of which we have need at present. A season of experiment in religious regulations must be a season of anxiety and apprehension. Our most implicit confidence in the honest intentions of those who legislate cannot make us forget that, after all, their united wisdom is but the wisdom of man. Therefore, while we wish them good luck in the name of the Lord, we cannot divest ourselves of all fear, lest, in their eagerness to secure advantages merely temporal, they should interfere with the more deliberate designs of Providence&#8212;of <hi rend="italic">that</hi> Providence which, by the wonderful events <hi rend="italic">that have come to pass</hi> within our memory, and under our own eyes, has seemed to say that our national prosperity is not likely to increase by any diminution of our vigilance against a Church from which our solemn and decided separation has been, if not the cause, certainly the contemporary, of every national superiority, if we posses any, in
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.004"/>
        
    pure morals, sound learning, and sincere piety.</p>
    
    <p><ref target="#hta.026.n02"></ref> Animadversions, however cautious or mild, on legal and political subjects, can produce no good from this place. It is probable that they are seldom uttered with impartiality&#8212;It is certain that they are never heard without prejudice. Whether we be capable or not, we are too frequently supposed unwilling to separate the general interests of Religion from the immediate interests of the Priesthood. Ungenerous as this imputation of narrow-mindedness may be, we can never prove its injustice, because we cannot establish an universal negative. To those who prevent us with suspicion, our purest arguments will seem tainted with selfishness. It is better, therefore, to refrain, even from good words, than that the Ministry be blamed.&#8212;Should our silence, our submission, our
  
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n02">Appendix, Note B.</note>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.005"/>  
    
    conscientious sufferings, be mistaken by men, it is a small thing to be judged by man. There is one who judgeth right.&#8212;Unto him all hearts are open, and he will equally accept our forwardness or our forbearance, if we be uniformly actuated by a desire of uniting the knowledge of his truth with peace and good will toward men. If there is to be a signal contest on points essential to the existence and extension of the true Faith, (and Prophecy seems to prepare us for it,) no political enactments can win or lose the victory. If the Lord be on our side, we need not fear what man can do unto us.</p>
    
    <p>That some Christian Communion in its present profession of Faith, and moral law, if not in its present form of establishment and discipline, will suddenly or gradually gain entire dominion over all others, is an opinion not hastily to be pronounced chimerical. Such a consummation is in harmony with all that we know of God's
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.006"/>
    
    dealings with Man. The rod of Aaron swallowed up the rods of the Mgicians. The world has never yet been without one Nation, or one Tribe, or one Family, with whom the Almighty has chosen to record his name. <hi rend="italic">As</hi> there ever has been, somewhere on Earth, one Faith and one form of Worship acceptable to the Lord, <hi rend="italic">so,</hi> doubtless, it <hi rend="italic">now</hi> is&#8212;<hi rend="italic">So</hi> will it continue to be, till all things are restored. The last enemy to be subdued in the Church is Schism. What church existing now on earth maybe the one approved, may be in all essentials most conformed to the finally-triumphant Church, is not fo rus to predicate. Yet where is the presumption, where the intolerance, in saying that it cannot be a Church, which, independent of innumerable minor impieties and absurdities, adheres pertinaciously to the following monstrous doctrines? That Men, instead of being, when they have done all, unprofitable servants, are capable of working out more than their own salvation. That
        
    <pb facs="hta.026.007"/>  
        
        human absolution is complete and sufficient. That <ref target="#hta.026.n03"></ref> tradition is of equal authority with Scripture. That persecution is acceptable to God. That, in the furtherance of its own tenets, all things are lawful. That not only is perjury pardonable, but deceit a duty. It is grievous to touch, even lightly, on such Anti-Christian doctrines. It may be said, such things out not to be so much as mentioned amongst us, for Charity's sake&#8212;nor should they be, nor need they be, if the Church which propagated such doctrines in the hour of its worldly ascendant, had ever been induced, by the lesson of adversity, or the light of conscience, to retract or reform the least defensible of them. Assuredly, then, we may predict that some Church, of very different tenets, will flourish on the earth at the great day of the Lord&#8212;Some Church whihc breathes a spirit of peace and purity, and universal love&#8212;A Church considerate,

        <note xml:id="hta.026.n03">Appendix, Note C.</note>   
  
    <pb facs="hta.026.008"/>
        
    and tolerant, in all things temporal, but in all things spiritual, incapable of compromise&#8212;A Church ambitious only of the Truth as it is in the Gospel, contending that Scripture containeth all things necessary to salvation, and calling on all its members, without respect of persons, to prove the faith which they profess by works of love and charity, by purity of thought, and righteousness of life.</p>
    <p>If, peradventure, God should be gracious unto us&#8212;If it be his design to perpetuate our Church, we know that nothing can prevail against it&#8212;neither powers, nor principalities, nor things present, nor things to come. Moreover, as the foolishness of God confounds the wisdom of the wise, it is not improbable that those very circumstances which, for a time, exalt the hopes of a hostile Church (for as a Church, it is hostile, however amiable or respectable be many of its votaries) will somehow be made a snare unto it&#8212;So that a man shall say&#8212;
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.009"/>
    
   "the things which have happened, have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the Gospel." And this confidence have we more strongly, inasmuch as the closer approximation of our Church to the principal graces of Christianity&#8212;to mercy, meekness, and forbearance, is made manifest by many important concessions already granted, and by a disposition, on adequate securities, to grant concessions still more important to those who hold our Communion in abhorrence. For the truth of this we appeal to the doctrines, the discipline, the decrees of those to whom we are called on to hold out the right hand of fellowship. Their consciences must tell them that they have already received from u stests of benignity, pledges of brotherhood, abandonment of advantage, and surrender of security, which their Church has never given, which it can never give, without renouncing every dogma, and reversing every decree, whereon it has erected its pretensions to supremacy.&#8212; 
   
    <pb facs="hta.026.010"/>
    
    AVoiding all bitterness of speech, our relative character and conduct cannot be more clearly or compendiously stated than by observing, that those to whom we are expected to grant everything, would not, in circumstances correspondingly reversed, grant anything. They would not do it&#8212;they could not do it, and be true to their most deliberate counsels, and most solemn professions.</p>
    <p>Probably there are many well-meaning persons who will say that charity, the very mark of our <hi rend="italic">calling,</hi> should prompt us to bury in silence, if not in oblivion, all the enormities exercised within these realms, by the Romish Church, against the Fathers of our own. When we forget the vital differences between our Church and theirs, then we shall easily forget the different conduct of each. And when we have learned to think these vital differences unimportant, then we shall have unlearned our Bible&#8212;and the sooner we are silent the
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.011"/>
    
    better for the Gospel, which doubtless some other nation will be selected to preach. But, till then, we must forget nothing&#8212;we must keep back nothing in the discharge of our duty to perform, as arduous as it is delicate. In the discharge of it we mus tnot put sweet for bitter, nor lend ourselves to the popular but compromising language of the passing hour. Charity certainly does require us to pardon a contrite, to embrace a repentant enemy. But does it require us to put arms into the hands of one who has never even pretended to renounce<ref target="#hta.026.n04"></ref> hostilities? It might be our duty to forget the atrocious sacrifice of a Latimer, a Ridley, and a Cranmer, if we had any good reason for thinking that the bigotry which lighted their piles had ever renounced its right, (were the power restored,) to light ours, and our children's, to the tenth generation. The fact is this, a fact to which many of
    
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n04">Appendix, Note D.</note>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.012"/>
    
    our unsuspecting fellow Protestants shut their eyes, but to which the eyes of the Romanists are never shut. The difference between their rule of Faith and ours is irreconcileable&#8212;the struggle interminable. It is a difference which has no parallel with any judicial, political, or territorial dispute. It is quite impossible to coalesce with that which is adverse in all its elements; it is impossible to treat with that which concedes nothing; it is impossible to ameliorate that which pronounces itself infallible; it is impossible not to be in danger from that which does not deny its hostile intentions. The danger to which we are now exposed is one, from which human laws cannot defend us: a danger which none can fight against successfully, but those who bear a higher commission than that of human appointment. The danger is to our Church. I do not mean merely ot its discipline and its establishment, for these, reasonable and venerable as they are, must not be insisted on as essential or unimprovable, but to the
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.013"/>
        
    true Church of Christ; we, my Brethren, who have solemnly devoted ourselves to the defence of the Gospel, are called on to combat for it. And ours will it be to preserve, together with the Gospel, all those advantages, moral and political, which are not the results of religious indifference, but of a zealous attachment to a Religion, which has endeavoured to purify itself from every doctrine, of questionable authority, and which rests its claims to Catholicism on a faithful version, and an apostolic construction of the Scriptures. </p>
    
    <p>While we most devoutly pray that our country may reap all the temporal benefits, which the most sanguine can expect, from the enlightened spirit of modern legislation, still must we warn the wisest of them not to calculate on permanent advantage, from any measure which regards, as a secondary consideration, the effects that may be produced on the integrity of our national religion. If they do, are they not, <choice><reg>however</reg><orig>how-
        
    <pb facs="hta.026.014"/>
        
        ever</orig></choice> unintentionally, fighting against God? It is not pious, and therefore not prudent, to expect his blessing, if we legislate on any other than religious principles. It is not pious, and therefore not rational to suppose that national prosperity needs any other support than that of a pure Religion. It is not pious, and therefore absurd to look for such support, in yielding to the prejudices of a Church from which we are separated and come out on points intimately connected with the honour and glory of God. Do we doubt the purity of our religion, or do we doubt his disposition to defend the nation which professes it, from the malice of all its adversaries? Let us beware lest such distrust provoke him to desert us&#8212;lest he say unto us "O! ye of little faith," and smite us with a curse. <ref target="#hta.026.n05"></ref>In whatever light the men of this world may have brought themselves to <choice><reg>contemplate</reg><orig>contem-
   
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n05">Appendix, Note E.</note>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.015"/>
            
            plate</orig></choice> the measure lately under discussion&#8212;<hi rend="italic">We,</hi> as the Ministers of God and stewards of his mysteries, have no option. So long as it is a measure of experiment, we must entertain alarm lest the cause of true religion suffer any let or hindrance. Our forefathers unquestionably had reason to regard the Romish Religion as inaccessible to any feeling of gratitude or forbearance. They legislated accordingly. Their judgment was guided by a strong light of recent experience. Their sufferings forced them to be cautious. The fruit of their caution has not been a national decay in political, intellectual, or religious preeminence. All useful arts, all liberal sciences have flourished.&#8212;And, above all, the spirit which diffuses the <ref target="#hta.026.n06"></ref>Word of God even to the ends of the world, has been cradled in these realms. But since some of our contemporaries have pronounced these cautions severe, and are so eager to
    
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n06">Appendix, Note F.</note>   
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.016"/> 
        
        reap the problematical advantages of a more confiding system, we must be the more watchful, and, like unto, men, prepared to meet the adversary. Upon ourselves alone, under the guidance of the Holy Spirit, are we to depend for the preservation of that Apostolic branch of Christianity planted in these realms; beneath the shelter of which, we have enjoyed statutes and judgments so righteous, and have had the Lord our God so nigh unto us in all things that we call upon him for. From the present moment to the end of his ministry, every Minister of our Church will do well to consider its inveterate enemy as at the gate of the camp, elate with success, and full of hope that he may make those apostate, whom he already regards as wavering.<ref target="#hta.026.n07"></ref> From the present moment our prevailing sentiment should be the fear of losing any one of our flock, through the
    
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n07">Appendix, Note G.</note>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.017"/>
        
    artifices of a religion peculiarly adapted to fasten on the superstition of the ignorant, and tamper with the back-slidings of the profligate. And these particular features of the Romish Church point out to us most clearly our duties as Ministers of a reformed one. Whatever of forbearance in our conversation, our discourses, our writings, we may have hitherto shewn, as due in Christian courtesy towards an enemy apparently prostrate, must now be laid aside. Henceforwards there ought not to be the shadow of wavering; we must not permit our sincerity and zeal to be suspected; we must put on armour, and keep it on; nay, we must arm others also; we must imprress on the hearts and minds of our flocks, our countrymen, and all the world, this great truth, that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are not in the slightest degree pledged, disposed, or capable of being disposed by the brightest prospect of political advantage, to concede one atom of the space which separates our Church from that of Rome. 
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.018"/>
        
        To this end it is ery advisable that every one of us, and particularly the younger members of our calling, should direct his studies, if not already so directed by the gathering danger, to those branches of professional knowledge, which will enable him to mark, discern, expound, and impress, on all committed to his charge, the irreconcileable differences of the two Churches. This will be very satisfactory, and not a tedious inquiry. The revealed word of God has drawn the broad line of distinction. Nor is it too much to assert, that the conditions of Salvation have not been more grossly mis-stated by its open enemies, than by the general councils of the Romish Church. Almost all that we need know, all that we need state on this subject, has been already carefully collected, and clearly set forth fro us, by the labour of a most learned <ref target="#hta.026.n08"></ref> Prelate, whose <choice><reg>arguments</reg><orig>argu-
   
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n08">Comparative View of the Churches of England and Rome, by the Right Rev. Herbert Marsh, Lord Bishop of Peterborough.</note>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.019"/>
    
    ments</orig></choice> are as unanswerable as his appeal is eloquent.<ref target="#hta.026.n09"></ref></p>
    
    <p>To spread such salutary knowledge, to circulate such triumphant productions of learning, combatting on the side of truth, let us not forget. This will be real charity; this will be to distribute, and to do good. Neither let us be seduced from warning adn exhorting all men, by the love of present ease, nor deterred by the dread of being called intolerant. An extreme sensibility to the opinions of the multitude is prejudicial to the firmness and simplicity of the clerical character. If we cannot preserve a due influence over our flocks, without a temporising conduct, their hearts are already wrong, and we the more loudly called on to put life and death before them. A 
        
    <note xml:id="hta.026.n09">"So conclusive, indeed, are his Lordshiy's reasonings, that on one occasion, they carried entire conviction to the mind of a person, who had been educated in the Romish Faith. This person was of mature age, clear judgment, correct morals, and considerable attainments. The circumstance came within the scope of my own observation."</note>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.020"/>
    
    pusillanimous apprehension of being called bigots is not less destructive of pure religion than bigotry itself, and the prevailing temper of the age seems to render it a much more probable extreme. Therefore, a very principal object of our efforts should be to prevent, if possible, a danger and indefinite liberality from becoming the characteristic of the rising generation&#8212;Under Providence we have the means. A very limited acquaintance with foreign kingdoms suffices to shew us, that the higher ranks of this country are distinguished from those of others, by soundness of principle, and nicety of moral sense. Are not these things so, because the education of our youth is for the most part confided to the Ministers of Religion? Great is the advantage, and heavy the responsibility of those, who thus have access to the minds of the rising generation, in a state of purity.</p>
    
    <p>The moment is arrived when every measure of pious precaution becomes the 
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.021"/>
    
    indispensable duty of all our schools and universities. If they aspire to the praise of teaching useful, they must be careful to teach religious learning. It should be their crown and excellence (for soon it will be their sole protection) to enrich the minds of their pupils with the knowledge of the Sacred Scriptures. Surely the volume of divine truth may profitably occupy some portion of those years, which, for the most part, hitherto, have been surrendered to the study of splended fiction. Instead of sacrificing all to form the taste and point the imagination, let a remnant be spared to strengthen the mind, and fix the principles. Instead of toiling continually over ancient lore, let them know what the wisest of those Ancients desired to know, and were not permitted. Let them be able to give an unanswerable reason for the faith which they profess, rejecting the traditions of men and doctrines of devils. And if to their faith they would add public virtue, let them be assured that they can never give
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.022"/>
    
    better proof of patriotism, than by shewing themselves pure Protestants, nor ever serve their country so effectually as by a jealous defence of that Religion, which has been teh foster mother of her greatness. That this is not vain boasting, we have the substantial evidence of things seen. Let us tell them to those who come after. Let them be taught, as soon as they are able to learn, that their country has advanced, beyond all example, in strength adn security at home&#8212;in power and consideration abroad, from the time that she separated herself from the Church of Rome&#8212;that she retrograded only when her councils and her rulers were tainted with the leaven of <hi rend="italic">that</hi> superstition&#8212;that Heaven, as if to mark a special providence over our reformed Church, vouchsafed to extend far beyond the usual limits of life, the reign of that revered, beloved, and lamented Monarch, who shewed himself its dauntless champion and inflexible protector. O! that a double
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.023"/>
    
    portion of his spirit may rest on all his race!</p>
    
    <p>And now my beloved reverend brethren, let me, in conclusion, entreat you to put no unfavourable construction on waht I have deemed it my duty to declare. Wrong me not by supposing that I have uttered one word in the tone of admonition&#8212;far otherwise: I doubt neither your zeal nor your discretion. Were you deficient in either, it would not be my province to comment thereon. If any increase of courage or caution were requisite, from no quarter would exhortation or admonition be so prompt, so powerful, or so welcome, as from our venerable visitor before who I now stand, giving an account of my doctrines.</p>
    
    <p>It has been my lot to see other countries calling themselves christian. To see, and shudder at the consequences, of a degraded and vacillating Church Establishment.&#8212;
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.024"/>

    That such States are hastening to moral ruin is no consolation, unless it be made a warning.&#8212;Be it our warning. Let us muse on these things till the fire kindle within us. Let us go forth together, nothing doubting but speaking with all boldness&#8212;let us not be afraid of doing too much, nor setting our cause too high. Half measures in religion, as in arms or legislation, are nothing worth&#8212;they never saved nor served a State. This has been proved, as far as regards our political prosperity, by the wonderful deliverances which have waited on our invincible perseverance. Why should not the same results, and more also, crown our struggle in the cause of Divine Truth? A very eloquent member of our senate once exclaimed&#8212;"Perish our commerce, let our constitution live." The vigor of the sentiment must be admired by many who many question its prudence. We have a better argument, a surer word of hope to rest on. We need not say "Perish our prosperity, let our Religion live," for we
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.025"/>
       
    are bold to say they cannot live apart. If our Religion fall, our country cannot stand, But our Religion will not fall, unless it be faulty&#8212;unless we be still in error&#8212;unless some other shall appear on earth, conforming itself more strictly to the revealed word. And this we know, because He is faithful who hath promised, "There shall be one Fold and one Shepherd."</p>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.026"/>
    
    <head>APPENDIX.</head>
    <head type="sub">NOTE A.</head>
    
    <p>THE predictions of our Saviour are distinguishable for the most part, from those of the Prophets, by a clearness and and precision of expression. The latter saw through a glass darkly, the former saw all things face to face. The safest way of construing his predictions is to take them literally. The things themselves must come to pass&#8212;of the times and seasons we know nothing.</p>
    <p>Though the fulfilment of this prediction may not require an universal similarity of discipline, nor even of opinion, on the mysterious points of the Christian Religion, yet does its accomplishment seem utterly incompatible with the continuance of such essential differences, in articles of faith, obligations of morality, and conditions of salvation, as now exist between the Romish Church, and every other calling itself Christian.</p>
    
    <head type="sub">NOTE B.</head>
    
    <p>In preserving their pulpits unpolluted by discussions, merely political, the Clergy do no more than their duty. Yet be it remembered, at the same time, that they, and they alone, are excluded from any other opportunity of raising their voice in a public character, on measures which
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.027"/>
    
    ought to be considered rather in a religious than a political light. The Clergy, and the Clergy only, are by law excluded, for life, from the great council of the people.&#8212;What degree of forbearance any order of men, similarly circumscribed, would be capable of, we cannot ascertain; but we must contend, that when the Clergy, alarmed as they are for the integrity of the National Church, do refrain from wielding their ablest weapon, lest they should appear to raise it from selfish motives, they are practicing a forbearance which cannot be imposed on the members of any other class of the community, and which ought to engage that community on the side of their spiritual pastors.</p>
    
    <head type="sub">NOTE C.</head>
    
    <p>And, it might be added, that the decrees of a General Council are of higher than either. The Church of Rome, in withholding the cup from the Laity, in contradiction ot the usage of the Primitive Church, and in defiance of Christ's command, justifies itself by the following expression, which, for impious absurdity, has not, we trust, its parallel in the records of the world:&#8212;"Holy Mother Church recognizes its own authority in the administration of the Sacraments."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Council of Trent.</hi></p>
    
    <head type="sub">NOTE D.</head>
    
    <p>We are frequently assured, by the advocates for Catholic Emancipation, that the Roman Catholics of the present day ought not to be judged, by the actions of their forefathers&#8212;that now they are as harmless as doves. We might answer, that assertions cannot be taken for proof, and that those who have now no power to persecute, would be fools indeed (which we do not take them to be), if they 
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.028"/>
        
    avowed the inclination. But our better answer is, that in the present question we have nothing to do with individuals of the Romish Church. It is the Church of Rome from which we demand some proof of abated ferocity, some pledge of reciprocal toleration. We must demadn in vain. The infallible cannot err, cannot alter, cannot repent.&#8212;The Church of Rome does not permit its children to exercise their own judgment, or their own feelings, on any point of severity or toleration.</p>
    <p>As the Church of Rome never has renounced its right to exterminate all heretics, we must presume that it cherishes, as dearly as ever, a right which it might have resigned so much to its own credit and advantage.</p>
    <p>It is therefore a very unlogical conclusion to suppose, that it <hi rend="italic">reserves</hi> such an alarming and offensive right, only for the sake of <hi rend="italic">not exercising</hi> it. A conscientious Roman Catholic, and no other needs emancipation, is as much bound to approve and inflict the severities of his Church, as he is to conform to its rites, and communicate in its Sacraments.</p>
    <p>Intolerance and persecution are so hateful, and so hostile to the religion of an English Protestant, that he is ever willing to hope they are equally hateful to others. With more magnanimity than prudence, he ascribes to all who call themselves Christians, the same feelings of benevolence and toleration which he cherishes himself, forgetting that his feelings are such, only because he is a Protestant.</p>
    
    <head type="sub">NOTE E.</head>
    
    <p>Among many other extraordinary arguments used by the advocates of Catholic Emancipation, the following proves the facility with which common sense is lost sight of, in the furtherance of a favourite Scheme:&#8212;"One consequence of the proposed emancipation," say they, "would be to bring
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.029"/>
    
    over to our Church many most respectable members of the Romish, who now adhere to it from a <hi rend="italic">point of honour."</hi> How many of these <hi rend="italic">respectable</hi> persons would be added ot our Church, by such a curious process of conversion, is difficult to calculate. It is not so difficult to determine what degree of relief or commiseration is due to the political and civil deprivations of those, whose attachment to any religion is a <hi rend="italic">point of honour.</hi> Those who use the above argument are probably not aware of the double contradiction which it seems to involve;</p>
    <p>1. That there can be no honour in religious hypocrisy, or even religious dissimulation.</p>
    <p>2. That if there were, it would be forfeited by the very acknowledgment of such deceit&#8212;and without such an acknowledgment from the dissemblers, the advocates of Catholic Emancipation have no right to assume the case.</p>
    
    <head type="sub">NOTE F.</head>
    
    <p>Whatever difference of opinion may exist on the ments of the Bible Society, as operating at home; there can be none as to the utility and necessity of its labours abroad.&#8212;It is the offspring of English Protestantism, and is therefore hateful to the Church of Rome. Up to a very late period, we believe to the present moment, a leading Roman Catholic State in Europe has refused admission to the Bible, because its priests have deliberately avowed that the diffusion of the Scriptures would be detrimental to their hierarchy.</p>
    <p>If we emancipate the Catholics, who is to emancipate the Bible?</p>
    
    <pb facs="hta.026.030"/>
    
    <head type="sub">NOTE G.</head>
    
    <p>If, under a mistaken notion, which we know many of the lower orders do already entertain, that the essential differences between the Churches of Rome and England would be done away by the proposed emancipation, any individual of our flocks should become a victim ot the arts of those, who are ever restless in the pursuit of proselytes, we are apt to think, that the promoters of the Bill in question would have more positive guilt to answer for, than could be counterbalanced by all the temporal benefits resulting therefrom to the empire, from the present moment to the end of the world.</p>
    
    <head type="sub">THE END.</head>


    
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


