<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.025" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">LECTURE XXI.</title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="jh">Harper, Jordan</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="project">hta.025</idno>
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-06"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

    <pb facs="hta.025.001"/>
    
        <head>LECTURE XXI.</head>
            <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, XLVIII. 11.</bibl><lb/>
                <hi rend="italic">And Israel said unto Joseph, I had not though so see thy face; and, lo! God hath showed me also thy seed.</hi>
             </head>
    
    <p>THE internal evidence of the truth of the Old
        as well as the New Testament, is by much too
        considerable to be overlooked. By internal evidence,
        of course, I mean those marks of <hi rend="italic">reality</hi>
        and <hi rend="italic">genuineness,</hi> which are produced by the
        probability, fitness, pertinence, connexion both
        of the speeches and actions therein occurring,
        and which are accommodated to the personages,
        the times in which they lived, the habits of
        their life, the circumstances which controlled,
        the motives which influenced them, in such a
        manner as no human invention has ever equalled,
        and no alteration could improve. Whoever
        is desirous of discovering, and capable of appreciating
        these marks of reality, these internal
        proofs of truth stamped on the Scriptures, no
        doubt, by the will and pmport of God who g-iveth
        us largely every method of improving our
    
    <pb facs="hta.025.002"/>
        
        faith, will find them no where more thickly
        sown than in the five concluding chapters of the
        book of Genesis. The collected wisdom of this
        world has not furnished in any other writings
        such an impressive description of every human
        feeling, whether it be of envy, cruelty, grief, resignation,
        gratitude, pardon, or piety, all working
        out one great scheme of good. </p>
    
    <p>When it was related to Jacob, that his favourite
        son, whom he had so long and deeply
        deplored, that Joseph was yet alive, the workings
        of his mind are represented with a brevity,
        force, and truth, shaming the most laboured
        efforts of other ancient historians. Let me place
        the very words before you: "Jacob's heart
        fainted, for he believed them not."&#8212;This disbelief
        was not a disbelief in the power of God,
        but proceeded from a proper sense of his own
        unworthiness. What had he done to receive
        such great reward? Why should the Lord
        turn his sorrow into joy like the rivers of the
        south? He was therefore like one who did
        dream; he had not dared to hope that he should
        ever see all his children's children and peace
        upon Israel. Of the same nature was the pious
        doubt which overwhelmed the faculties of the
        disciples (when their crucified Redeemer reappeared
        among them), while they believed not for
        joy. Anon, however, when his sons had <choice><reg>repeated</reg><orig>repeat-
            
    <pb facs="hta.025.003"/>
            
        ed</orig></choice> to him their wonderful tidings, and confirmed
        their truth by showing the presents of which
        themselves were bearers, then the spirit of Jacob
        their father revived; and Israel said, " It is
        enough; Joseph my son is yet alive: I will go
        and see him before I die."</p>
    
        <p>Prosperity of any sort is a great trial of the
        heart, and indeed a very accurate test in general,
        whether it be well with God. The gift
        does not always remind us of the Giver. When
        we are magnified by any sudden visitation of
        good, be it ours to magnify the Lord; and when
        our spirit revives from the conflict of doubt,
        and swells into joy, let it habitually rejoice in
        the Lord our Saviour. Adversity seldom fails
        to cast us on our knees; for, when human
        friends forsake or look cool, the heart in very
        bitterness, as well as destitution, seeketh for a
        heavenly friend. But as Solomon says to those
        of immature years, "Remember thy Creator in
        the days of thy youth;" so docs the law of the
        Gospel, which is greater than Solomon, say
        unto all, Remember thy Creator in the day of
        rejoicing, lest your triumph be made a snare
        unto you. Jacob did remember the Lord with
        his whole heart at this most critical moment.
        He did not venture to indulge even what appeared
        to be the natural fondness of a parent,
        without mixing with it a truly pious feeling.
        
    <pb facs="hta.025.004"/>        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        </p>


</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


