<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.018" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="hb">Borrell, Hannah</name> <!-- if you are not Jordan Harper, change to your initials and name -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
    <idno type="project">hta.018</idno> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-02"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change> <!-- replace with correct name and date -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<!-- transcribe lecture here -->
    <!-- HELPFUL TIPS!
    
    new page: <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/> replace the x's with the file number and then the page number, should correspond with the file names in the sharepoint JPEG file folder
    headings: <head>HEADING IV.</head>
    subheadings: <head type="sub">less aggressive heading</head>
    linebreak: <lb/> use whenever there is a linebreak, usually common with subheadings or headings on the first page of a lecture
    paragraphs: <p></p> example: <p>all my awesome text, yippee</p>
    em dash: &#8212;
    italicized text: <hi rend="italic"></hi> example: <hi rend="italic">text that is italicized</hi>
    stupid words that are cut off at the end of a page: 
    
    <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice>
    
    
    
    -->

<pb facs="hta.018.001"/>
    
    <head>LECTURE XIV.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, XXVII. PART OF VER. 36.</bibl><lb/>
        <hi rend="italic"></hi>He hath supplanted me these two times: he took away my birthright; and, behold, now he hath taken away my blessing.</head>
    <p>Such was the accusation made by Esau against his brother Jacob, in the moment of bitterness, disappointement, and resentment. The charge was a heavy one. If true, the relationship of Jacob to the complainant added considerably to the weight of the crime. But if the accusation was not strictly true, if not more than half of it was true, if the other grief of which Esau complained was in fact altogether brought by him on his own head, we must not suffer ourselves to commiserate the case of the elder brother, nor join with him in obloquy against the younger hastily. Let us, therefore, inform ourselves accurately as to the circumstances which produced Esau's complaint; and the more so, because I suspect that a superficial and hasty perusal of the narrative delivered by Moses, has had frequently the effect of producing not only an excessive and unjustifiable sympathy with
    
<pb facs="hta.018.002"/>    
    Esau; but also, as connected therewith, a comdemnation of Jacob's conduct as scarcely reconcilable with the share of God's favour that he enjoyed through life. Let us see how these things really were, and why they were related to us by one, Moses, who might, if judged of as a national historian, be well inclined to bury in oblivian any questionable conduct of his progenitor.</p>
    <p>1. When Esau asserted that Jacob had stolen from him his birthright, he asserted what he knew was false. He had himself sold it for a despicable consideration. From the nature of his charge against Jacob, it is evident that he was not ignorant of the value of it. He dwells on it as a great deprivation, as one to be ranked with his father Isaac's blessing; yet in the moment of sensual temptation he had sold it for a mess of pottage. It was not, therefore, without great propriety that the inspired historian records to us the deliberate slight which Esau put on the promises of God, as regarding Abraham and Isaac's seed for ever. We read as follows, in the very last words of the preceding chapter: <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.018.q001" source="kjv">"Thus Esau despised his birthright."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.018.q001" resp="#eds">Genesis 25:34</bibl> Esau, therefore, is guilty of gross falsehood when he charges his brother with having stolen his birthright. Nor does his crime herein consist of falsehood alone: he not only accuses Jacob
    
<pb facs="hta.018.003"/>    
    of doing what he did not do, but passes by with intemperate ferocity and blind passion the opportunity of expressing any sense of his own guilt in having slighted such a distinction, and thus shut the door of pardon, and sealed God's wrath against him.</p>
    <p></p>










</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


