<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.022" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="hb">Borrell, Hannah</name> <!-- if you are not Jordan Harper, change to your initials and name -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
    <idno type="project">hta.022</idno> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-07"><name sameAs="#hb"/> transcribed and encoded</change> <!-- replace with correct name and date -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<!-- transcribe lecture here -->
    <!-- HELPFUL TIPS!
    
    new page: <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/> replace the x's with the file number and then the page number, should correspond with the file names in the sharepoint JPEG file folder
    headings: <head>HEADING IV.</head>
    subheadings: <head type="sub">less aggressive heading</head>
    linebreak: <lb/> use whenever there is a linebreak, usually common with subheadings or headings on the first page of a lecture
    paragraphs: <p></p> example: <p>all my awesome text, yippee</p>
    em dash: &#8212;
    italicized text: <hi rend="italic"></hi> example: <hi rend="italic">text that is italicized</hi>
    stupid words that are cut off at the end of a page: 
    
    <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice>
    
    
    
    -->

<pb facs="hta.022.001"/>
    
    <head>LECTURE XVIII.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, XXXVII. 3, 4.</bibl><lb/>
        <hi rend="italic"></hi>Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his children, because he was the son of his old age; and he made him a coat of many colours: and when his brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren, they hated him, and could not speak peaceably unto him.</head>

    <p>Two hundred years nearly had elapsed between the time of God's original promise made to Abraham, and the era which we are now about to consider&#8212;a period replete with proofs of God's abundant loving-kindness, mercy, and truth. The family which he had selected to be agents of his mysterious protection, the chosen guardians of his oracles, the sole possessors of his law, and the typical representatives on earth of his people in a heavenly kingdom: this family had been selected, propogated, and preserved, on more than one occasion, by miracle. Neither the fraud nor the violence of surrounding tribes, nor yet the still more threatening spirit of <choice><reg>family</reg><orig>fa-
        
<pb facs="hta.022.002"/>
    mily</orig></choice> dissesion, had prevailed against its safety, sucess, and establishment.</p>
    <p>After such a continuance of God's general protection and particular interference on every important occasion, Jacob might very excusably consider himself to have already acquired in Canaan the promised resting-place for the sole of his foot. He might reasonably enough suppose that the Lord was now about to reward him with good for all the adversity of his early life; and that, by a gradual extension of his children's children, God would perform the truth which he had sworn unto Abraham from the days of old. God had indeed shown unto Jacob what was good; he had required at his hands humility, obedience, and mercy. It does not appear that Jacob had on any occasion been found wanting in the balance. But the beloved of God are tried in the repetition of adversity, even as gold is tried seven times in the fire. It was enacted of old, that no man should enter into God's kingdom except through much tribulation.</p>
    <p>There were many reasons why it should be most congruous to God's counsels that Jacob should reside in Canaan sufficiently long to conceive himself, and to impart to his sons, a predilection for it, as for the land of promise; that he and his whole family should then be fore
    
<pb facs="hta.022.003"/>    
    a while removed from it: so taht during the period of their absence they might cherish a remembrance of God's promise, impress on their minds the annexed condition of obedience on their side, previous to a gift on his, and gather unto themselves sufficient strength and force to return unto it as conquerors, expelling before their face the idolaters who had hostile possession. That Jacob, therefore, should remove with his family into some other country, was highly expedient; yet nothing appeared less likely in the ordinary course of things, if he were left to the workings of his own inclination. Let us observe how God brought about by means extremely simple, events the most extraordinary.</p>
    <p>The history of Joseph and his brethren possesses every circumstance to invite and reward our closest attention. Though an instance of particular providence, it is an epitome of what is always going on in every part of the world at every moment. God is always bringing good out of evil. The righteous man is never forsaken, and the proud doer is always plenteously rewarded. Moreover, the abode of the Israelites for a season in Egypt, represents, 1st, the general state of sin and darkness, that wretched and cheerless valley, in which all the children of men were sitting, until the light of the Gospel
    
<pb facs="hta.022.004"/>    
    became the pillar of fire, to illuminate their paths, and point out a return to that heavenly Canaan, which had been so long lost, as to be by most forgotten. It represents, 2dly, the abode of man, even Christian man, on earth, which is a captivity of sin and a bondage of the soul, until such time as, after many trials and a life of pilgrimage, during which he is often brought into despair, and often refuses all manner of comfort, the grace of the Gosepl at length drops manna on his hungry and thirsting soul, and he being made acceptable by faith below, is admitted into Jerusalem above, and receiveth his portion with the spirits of the just made perfect in heaven. We must, therefore, consider the history of Joseph as continually offering to us subjects for moral reflection and spiritual consolation; setting before us lively examples of good and evil consequence, arising from the indulgence or government of our passions as human beings, commanded to love, and forbidden to evil entreat each other; setting also before our eyes, the early intimation which God was pelased to give to the Jews, that it was ever his will to save many by the mediation of one, and that it was expedient for the innocent to suffer for the guilty, the just for the unjust. We must, therefore, look on Jacob and the brethren of Joseph as men of like passions with ourselves, severally drawing
    
 <pb facs="hta.022.005"/>   
    down on themselves, even in this world, the natural and due consequences of their weaknesses and crimes; yet, nevertheless, involuntarily working out the will of god; reaping, as far as regarded themselves, vexation, sorrow, fear, and confusion, where they had sown injustice, malice, revenge, and falsehood; but still augmenting the glory of God, declaring his marvellous works among all nations, and that he is the God of vengeance to all who touch his anointed or do his prophets harm.</p>
    <p><quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.022.q001" source="kjv">"And Israel loved Joseph more than all his children, because he was the son of his old age."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.022.q001" resp="#eds">Genesis 37:3</bibl>&#8212;Such is the plain statement of the historian, of the inspired historian, Moses; the fourth in descent from Jacob, of whom he wrote, and therefore writing of events fresh in the memory of all. There can be no doubt of the truth of the statement; for, not being favourable to Jacob, it is little likely that it should have been wantonly made by his own descendant. The preference which Jacob felt for Joseph is also very intelligibly accounted for. It was a natural weakness, as the observation of every day most unhappily enables us to perceive; but, although natural, although very frequent, not a whit the less a weakness, not a whit the less pregnant with bitter consequences.</p>
    
<pb facs="hta.022.006"/>
    <p>The preference which is felt, almost inevitably felt, by parents for one child above the rest, even when founded on a demonstrable superiority of talent, temper, and conduct, is not commendable, and generally leads both parents and their offspring, in the sequel, very far from the paths of equity, and consequently from the object of their pursuit, namely, happiness. But when this preference has no better basis than that assigned by Moses to Jacob, it is rightly punished by such rewards as it brought on him. FOr more than twenty years did Jacob lament the supposed death of Joseph; and so heavily, that, by his own avowal, it seems to have stamped an indelible character of wretchedness on his life, when he looked at it in the retrospect; for his answer to Pharoah when he inquired the vulnerable patriarch's age, was, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.022.q002" source="kjv">"Few and evil have the days of the years of my life been, and have not attained unto the days of the years of the life of my fathers."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.022.q002" resp="#eds">Genesis 47:9</bibl> Jacob here plainly connects the shortness of his life with its unhappiness; and that the extraordinary fate of Joseph caused the unhappiness, we may conclude, because, in the subsequent chapters, he frequently refers to it with bitterness, and because it was fresh to his mind, even when the horrors of famine stared him in the face, and threatened annihilation to himself, and his sons, and his daughters, and their little ones. On
    
<pb facs="hta.022.007"/>    
    </p>







</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


