<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.4.0.0/tei_all.rng"  type="xml"?>
<TEI xml:id="hta.010" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main"></title>
<author></author>
<principal>White, Laura Mooneyham</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcription, encoding, proofreading</resp>
<name xml:id="hb">Borrell, Hannah</name> <!-- if you are not Jordan Harper, change to your initials and name -->
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2026</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Henry Thomas Austen</authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
    <idno type="project">hta.010</idno> <!-- replace "hta.00x" with filename -->
<availability>
<p>This edition is licensed under a Creative Commons Licence (available at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). You are free: to copy,
distribute, display, and perform the work, and to make derivative works under the following conditions: you must attribute the work in the manner
specified by the licensor; you may not use this work for commercial purposes; if you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may distribute
the resulting work only under a license identical to this one. For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others the license terms of
this work. Any of these conditions can be waived if you get permission from the licensor. Your fair use and other rights are in no way affected by
the above.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note/>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl type="print">
<author></author>
<title></title>
<respStmt>
<resp></resp>
<name></name>
</respStmt>
<pubPlace></pubPlace>
<publisher></publisher>
<date></date>
</bibl>
<msDesc>
<msIdentifier>
<repository></repository>
<collection></collection>
<idno type="callnumber"></idno>
<idno type="box"></idno>
<idno type="folder"></idno>
</msIdentifier>
</msDesc>

</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="lcsh" n="keywords">
<term/>
</keywords>
</textClass>

</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-02"><name sameAs="#jh"/> transcribed and encoded</change> <!-- replace with correct name and date -->
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>


<div type="sermon">

<!-- transcribe lecture here -->
    <!-- HELPFUL TIPS!
    
    new page: <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/> replace the x's with the file number and then the page number, should correspond with the file names in the sharepoint JPEG file folder
    headings: <head>HEADING IV.</head>
    subheadings: <head type="sub">less aggressive heading</head>
    linebreak: <lb/> use whenever there is a linebreak, usually common with subheadings or headings on the first page of a lecture
    paragraphs: <p></p> example: <p>all my awesome text, yippee</p>
    em dash: &#8212;
    italicized text: <hi rend="italic"></hi> example: <hi rend="italic">text that is italicized</hi>
    stupid words that are cut off at the end of a page: 
    
    <choice><reg>ascertaining</reg><orig>ascer-
    
    <pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/>
    
    taining</orig></choice>
    
    
    
    -->

<pb facs="hta.010.001"/>
    
    <head>LECTURE VI.</head>
    <head type="sub"><bibl>GENESIS, XII. PART OF VER. 3.</bibl><lb/>
    <hi rend="italic">And in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed.</hi></head>

    <p>Such were the words which were spoken to Abraham by the Lord. The tenour of the promises is no less important to us than to the children of Israel, who, as descendants of Abraham, considered themselves sole heirs of the promise. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q001" source="kjv">"We, by adoption," says the Apostle, "are become the children of the promise, and joint heirs with Christ of the kingdom of heaven."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q001" resp="#eds">Romans 8:15-17</bibl> If then, all the families of the earth are blessed in the seed of Abraham, it must be worth while for all of us to inquire with particular attention into every circumstance of Abraham's life and character, which the sacred historian has recorded. Nor can there be a stronger proof that such an inquiry was expected on the part of Moses, and, consequently, approved on that of Heaven, than the copiousness and minuteness of his narrative in all that regards this patriarch. We will, therefore, first inform
    
<pb facs="hta.010.002"/>    
    ourselves on the point of Abraham's genealogy. To the three sons of Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japhet, various parts of the ancient world were severally assigned either by mutual agreement or the express injunction of Noah. the descendents of Japhet seem to have spread themselves westward through Europe, or, in the words of Scripture, the isles of the Gentiles. We may here observe, that the distribution of Japhet's family is very briefly mentioned; the reason is obvious; they were not to act any very material part in the history of the Jews, for whose instruction and guidance Moses chiefly wrote, so long as that people retained any claim to the title of a nation; while the genealogy and future possessions of Ham, though accursed of his father, are detailed very much at lenght. We are presented with an account of many generations, and the names of several nations which they founded, and cities which they built, to the end that we might fully perceive the faithfullness of God's threats, as well as his promises; and know that the posterity of Ham were the Canaanite, the Jebusite, the Amorite, the Hivite, and the Phillistine, with many other equally idolatrous tribes, who nearly one thousand years after the sin of their undutiful progenitor, fell before the hand of the Lord by the sword of Joshua, David, and other appointed instruments of his will. To shem, as the <choice><reg>firstborn</reg><orig>first-
            
<pb facs="hta.010.003"/>
        born</orig></choice>, God gave for a season the privilege of his birthright. The eastern countries beyond the region of Ham were probably the first possessions; the beautiful plains of Shinar, through which the Tigris runs, comprehending the country of Eden, where Paradise had been situated. But the most valuable privilege of birthright was, that from Shem should in fact descend that favoured Being, to whom the promises of God were to be much more fully detailed, much more frequently repeated, and much more clearly explained, than they had ever before been&#8212;namely, Abraham, the father of the faithful. Moses, therefore, with the utmost precision, delivers an uninterrupted genealogy of nine generations, from Shem to Abraham. The consistency of the Lord is thus made manifest in dispensing upon Abraham and his seed, so long as they should be obedient, those blessings which he promised to Shem in consideration of his pious and dutiful conduct, in concealing the errors of the a father. Nor will it show the consistency of God less plainly, that to Japhet also it had been promises that he should be ENLARGED. His ulterior enlargement, it seems, was commenced as early even as the first intimation of Shem's immediate prosperity;&#8212;the enlargement and extension of Christianity among the western nations was predicted precisely at
    
<pb facs="hta.010.004"/>    
    the same amount as the previous election of the Jews; and the same design was afterwards plainly typified at least twice, even in the very families of the patriarchs, when Isaac was preferred to Ishmael, and Jacob to Esau.</p>
    <p>Before we proceed to detail the singular and important events which distinguished the life and conduct of Abraham, it may be right to remind ourselves, that they have been handed down to us for two principal purposes: the first is, to assure us that God from the beginning had determined on the salvation of mankind, by the sacrifice of a pure and sufficient victim: the second is, to teach us the inseperable union between obeying God's commandments and believing in his promises; in other words, the inseperable compact between good works and fervent faith, which was expected from the children of circumcision, and which will not be dispensed with in the better instructed children of the Gospel:therefore the obedience and the faith of Abraham are what we are to regard as chiefly contributive to our edification.</p>
    <p>The first test of obedience which was demanded of Abraham by the Lord was such as in those times must have been severer than we now perhaps are fully aware of. It was, to <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q002" source="kjv">"get him out of his country, and from his kindred, and from his father's house, unto a land which was
    
<pb facs="hta.010.005"/>   
        to be shown him."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q002" resp="#eds">Genesis 12:1</bibl>Such was the peremptory word of the Lord. Let is be observed, that when the command was given, it was not accompanied with any intimation where that land was to be, under what climate, of what quality, whether near or remote, friendly or hostile. As far as Abraham's feelings and knowledge were concerned, it was to him, as when the angel with the falming sword expelled his first parents from Paradise. The whole world was before him&#8212;exile seemed certain, repose or advantage very doubtful. And, as I before said, there were at that period of the world habits, customs, and feelings which made the seperation of a patriarchal family much more grievous than can well be understood in the present state of society. Better wer it, perhaps, for the virtue of society, if men did not so easily break the bonds of parental, filial, and fraternal affection. In proportion as men strip themselves of what they call the weakness of natural affection, it is to be feared that they depart from the love of all simplicity, consequently from the love of godliness and God; and whilst they proudly boast themselves of a conquest over prejudices, they in fact are, in the language of an Apostle, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q003" source="kjv">"searing their consciences with a red-hot iron."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q003" resp="#eds">1 Timothy 4:2</bibl> Let those who enjoy the blessing of domestic happiness, diffused liberally and revolving fithfully through the various parts of an extended
    
<pb facs="hta.010.006"/>    
        circle, estimate its value by recalling to mind that God proposed it as a sacrifice to Abraham, that he should get him out from his kindred and from his father's house. To this commandment, as a trial of his obedience, God did also annex a promise of most extensive, boundless, and everlasting blessing, both as a trial and reward of his faith. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q004" source="kjv">"And I will make thee a great nation, and I will bless thee, and make thy name great; and thou shalt be a blessing: and I will bless them that bless thee, and curse him that curseth thee: and in thee shall all families of the earth be blessed."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q004" resp="#eds">Genesis 12:2</bibl> The latter words of this promise are the foundation on which we Christians have built our hopes. If the words mean any thing, they must mean, and from the first they did mean, that the erection of Abraham's immediate posterity into a nation, the increase of their numbers, the extension of their dominion, the vigour of their arms under David, and the splendour of their kingdom under Solomon, were to be but a very partial fulfilment of God's covenant with Abraham. So far were these things from being an universal blessing to all the families of the earth, that they were destructive to many nations, unknown to others, and even to the Jews themselves a very temporary and brief donation. The truth is, that God never intended to reward even the Jews by worldly prosperity only. However
    
<pb facs="hta.010.007"/>    
    they may have misunderstood, and do misunderstand, the scope of God's promise to Abraham, there is not the least doubt, from his subsequent conduct, but that he had a full faith in the extension and universality of that blessing which was typified in the welfare of his own peculiar family; though even he might not, as he needed not, know the particular means of grace, or predestined hope of glory. He believed, which was better than knowledge: to him was faith attributed for righteousness; which knowledge never yet was to any one.</p>
    <p><quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q005" source="kjv">"So Abraham departed, as the Lord had spoken unto him."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q005" resp="#eds">Genesis 12:4</bibl>&#8212;From this expression we collect, that he did it readily and cheerfully, that the voice of the Lord was the <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q006" source="kjv">"staff of his journey and the star of his following."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q006" resp="#eds">Matthew</bibl> The kindness of Abraham's nature, and the concern which he felt for the welfare of all over whom he could exercise control, or to whom he could afford protection, was exemplified on this occasion; as afterwards on many others. He took with ihm Lot, the son of his deceased brother Haran, partly, doubtless, to keep him steady in the worship of the true God, from which he might have wandered, had he been left in Mesopotamia; and partly, perhaps, that he might, peradventure, be partaker of that prosperity which the Lord had promised to himself. <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q007" source="kjv">"They
    
<pb facs="hta.010.008"/>    
    went into the land of Canaan, and passed through it, for the Canaanite was then in the land."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q007" resp="#eds">Genesis 12:6</bibl> In the course of these journeyings, the Lord appeared to Abraham, and unequivocally promised him that this very land, occupied as it now was by a tribe certainly not friendly to the family or the religion of Abraham, should hereafter be the possessions of his seed. Nothing could be less likely to human judgment; but Abraham, it is plain, put full confidence in the Lord, and gave himself up to be guided by his providence. he did not attempt to fix himself in any spot; he did not enter into the cities, or associate himself with those who inhabited them, and who might have seduced him from the Lord. He continued to lead a pastoral life, a life of peace and purity, abounding in works of hospitality, and never forgettting to raise an altar to the Lord at all his resting-places. About this time he was obliged to journey into Egypt, for a season, to avoid a famine which vexed the parts of Canaan. This probably was a type of that which was afterwards to befall the children of Israel. Pharaoh, innocently detaining Sarai, the wife of Abraham, was plagued by the Lord, and on that very account of Abraham subsequently departed out of Egypt much richer than he had entered it, in sheep, and oxen, and servants, and all which constituted the wealth of those times. In like manner, a famine carried down Jacob and his sons to Egypt. Their

<pb facs="hta.010.009"/>
    descendants were evilly entreated by another Pharaoh; and yet, by the special interference of God, from this very tyranny <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q008" source="kjv">"it came to pass, that when they were thrust out from the land, they found favour in the eyes of the Egyptians, and received from them jewels of silver and of gold;"</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q008" resp="#eds">Exodus 12:35-36</bibl> so that they are said to have spoiled the Egyptians.</p>
    <p>After Abraham's return from Egypt into the land of Canaan, increase of numbers made it expedient that he and Lot should seperate for the better sustenance of their respective trains. Though the masters were well disposed towards each other, the servants were not; there was strife between the herdsmen of Abraham and those of Lot. The conduct of Abraham, on this occasion, deserves our recollection: it showeth, that he then acknowledged the principles of the Gospel; his sentiments and his language prove the truth of our Saviour's words, when he said, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q009" source="kjv">"Verily I say unto you, that Abraham saw my day, and rejoiced at it."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q009" resp="#eds">John 8:56</bibl>&#8212;Abraham said unto Lot, <quote type="biblical" xml:id="hta.010.q010" source="kjv">"Let there be no strife I pray thee, between thee and me, or between thy herdsmen and my herdsmen, for we be brethren."</quote><bibl corresp="#hta.010.q010" resp="#eds">Genesis 13:8</bibl>&#8212;O! what a lesson to his perverse descendants! What a lesson to every one who professes the peaceable, the placable, the self-denying doctrines of Christ, and yet is <choice><reg>constantly</reg><orig>con-
        
<pb facs="hta.00x.00x"/>
    stantly</orig></choice> ready to give and receive affront, to strickle for doubtful claims, contend for worthless rights, and even take part in the petty and contemptible animosities of their descendants, whom they ought to repress by their authority, and shame by their example. <bibl>(Ver. 9.)</bibl> Abraham and Lot seperated: the latter most unwisely mixed himself with the cities of the plain of Sodom and Gomorrah, thereby, in a great degree, deserting the protection of God, and tempting that providence which was afterwards extended in his favour, chiefly for Abraham's sake. Abraham continued to keep himself seperate from the contact of the idolatrous, to dwell in his tent, and build his altar to the Lord. It is to be remarked, that, after the separation of Abraham and Lot, God renewed the promise of Canaan to the former alone. <bibl>(Verses 14, 15, 16, 17.)</bibl> This was divine intimation, that the descendants of Lot were not included in the promise; we know that they were Moab and Ammon, who founded idolatrous nations, and fell before Israel. The more minutely we consider these workings of the Lord, the more clearly shall we see the harmony existing between his earliest and his latest councils; and the more readily shall we confess, that when he sendeth out his voice, it is a mighty voice, penetrating unto the ends of the world, and proclaiming the decrees of eternity.</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>


